<country>
   <name>Chad</name>
   <section title="Photos of Chad"/>
   <section title="Introduction">
      <subsection title="Background">Chad emerged from a collection of powerful states that
controlled the Sahelian belt starting around the 9th
century. These states focused on controlling trans-Saharan trade
routes and profited mostly from the slave trade. The Kanem-Bornu
Empire, centered around the Lake Chad Basin, existed between the
9th and 19th centuries, and during its peak,
the empire controlled territory stretching from southern Chad to
southern Libya and included portions of modern-day Algeria,
Cameroon, Nigeria, Niger, and Sudan. The Sudanese warlord Rabih
AZ-ZUBAYR used an army comprised largely of slaves to conquer the
Kanem-Bornu Empire in the late 19th century. In
southeastern Chad, the Bagirmi and Ouaddai (Wadai) kingdoms emerged
in the 15th and 16th centuries and lasted
until the arrival of the French in the 19th and
20th centuries. France began moving into the region in
the late 1880s and defeated the Bagirmi kingdom in 1897, Rabih
AZ-ZUBAYR in 1900, and the Ouddai kingdom in 1909. In the arid
regions of northern Chad and southern Libya, an Islamic order
called the Sanusiyya (Sanusi) relied heavily on the trans-Saharan
slave trade and had upwards of 3 million followers by the 1880s.
The French arrived in the region in the early 1900s and defeated
the Sanusiyya in 1910 after years of intermittent war. By 1910,
France had incorporated the northern arid region, the Lake Chad
Basin, and southeastern Chad into French Equatorial Africa.
 Chad achieved its independence in 1960 and saw three decades of
instability, oppressive rule, civil war, and a Libyan invasion.
With the help of the French military and several African countries,
Chadian leaders expelled Libyan forces during the 1987 "Toyota
War," so named for the use of Toyota pickup trucks as fighting
vehicles. In 1990, Chadian general Idriss DEBY led a rebellion
against President Hissene HABRE. Under DEBY, Chad drafted and
approved a constitution and held elections in 1996. DEBY led the
country until April 2021 when he was killed during a rebel
incursion. Shortly after his death, a group of military officials -
led by former President DEBY’s son, Mahamat Idriss DEBY - took
control of the government. The military officials dismissed the
National Assembly, suspended the Constitution, and formed a
Transitional Military Council while pledging to hold democratic
elections in October 2022.Chad faces widespread poverty, an economy severely weakened by
low international oil prices, and rebel and terrorist-led
insurgencies in the Lake Chad Basin. Additionally, northern Chad
has seen several waves of rebellions since 1998. In late 2015, the
government imposed a state of emergency in the Lake Chad Basin
following multiple attacks by the terrorist group Boko Haram, now
known as ISIS-West Africa. In mid-2015, Boko Haram conducted
bombings in N'Djamena. In late 2019, the Chadian government also
declared a state of emergency in the Sila and Ouaddai regions
bordering Sudan and in the Tibesti region bordering Niger where
rival ethnic groups are still fighting. The army has suffered heavy
losses to Islamic terror groups in the Lake Chad Basin. In March
2020, Islamic militants attacked a Chadian military camp in the
Lake Chad Basin and killed nearly 100 soldiers; it was the
deadliest attack in the history of the Chadian military.</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Geography">
      <subsection title="Location">Central Africa, south of Libya</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geographic coordinates">15 00 N, 19 00 E</subsection>
      <subsection title="Map references">Africa</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area">total: 1.284 million sq km<br/>
         <br/>
land: 1,259,200 sq km<br/>
         <br/>
water: 24,800 sq km<br/>country
comparison to the world: 22</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area - comparative">almost nine times the size of New York state; slightly more than
three times the size of California</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land boundaries">total: 6,406 km<br/>
         <br/>
border countries (6): Cameroon 1,116 km; Central
African Republic 1,556 km; Libya 1,050 km; Niger 1,196 km; Nigeria
85 km; Sudan 1,403 km</subsection>
      <subsection title="Coastline">0 km (landlocked)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maritime claims">none (landlocked)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">tropical in south, desert in north</subsection>
      <subsection title="Terrain">broad, arid plains in center, desert in north, mountains in
northwest, lowlands in south</subsection>
      <subsection title="Elevation">highest point: Emi Koussi 3,445 m<br/>
         <br/>
lowest point: Djourab 160 m<br/>
         <br/>
mean elevation: 543 m</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural resources">petroleum, uranium, natron, kaolin, fish (Lake Chad), gold,
limestone, sand and gravel, salt</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">agricultural land: 39.6% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
arable land: 3.9% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent crops: 0% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent pasture: 35.7% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
forest: 9.1% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
other: 51.3% (2018 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Irrigated land">300 sq km (2012)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major lakes (area sq km)">fresh water lake(s): Lake Chad (endorheic lake
shared with Niger, Nigeria, and Cameroon) - 10,360-25,900 sq
km<br/>
note - area varies by season and year to year</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Niger (2,261,741 sq km)<br/>
Internal (endorheic basin) drainage: Lake Chad (2,497,738
sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major aquifers">Lake Chad Basin, Nubian Aquifer System</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">the population is unevenly distributed due to contrasts in
climate and physical geography; the highest density is found in the
southwest, particularly around Lake Chad and points south; the dry
Saharan zone to the north is the least densely populated as shown
in this <br/>population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural hazards">hot, dry, dusty harmattan winds occur in north; periodic
droughts; locust plagues</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geography - note">note 1: Chad is the largest of Africa's 16
landlocked countriesnote 2: not long ago - geologically speaking -
what is today the Sahara was green savannah teeming with wildlife;
during the African Humid Period, roughly 11,000 to 5,000 years ago,
a vibrant animal community, including elephants, giraffes, hippos,
and antelope lived there; the last remnant of the "Green Sahara"
exists in the Lakes of Ounianga (oo-nee-ahn-ga) in northern Chad, a
series of 18 interconnected freshwater, saline, and hypersaline
lakes now protected as a World Heritage sitenote 3: Lake Chad, the most significant water
body in the Sahel, is a remnant of a former inland sea, paleolake
Mega-Chad; at its greatest extent, sometime before 5000 B.C., Lake
Mega-Chad was the largest of four Saharan paleolakes that existed
during the African Humid Period; it covered an area of about
400,000 sq km (150,000 sq mi), roughly the size of today's Caspian
Sea</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="People and Society">
      <subsection title="Population">17,963,211 (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 67</subsection>
      <subsection title="Nationality">noun: Chadian(s)<br/>
         <br/>
adjective: Chadian</subsection>
      <subsection title="Ethnic groups">Sara (Ngambaye/Sara/Madjingaye/Mbaye) 30.5%,
Kanembu/Bornu/Buduma 9.8%, Arab 9.7%, Wadai/Maba/Masalit/Mimi 7%,
Gorane 5.8%, Masa/Musseye/Musgum 4.9%, Bulala/Medogo/Kuka 3.7%,
Marba/Lele/Mesme 3.5%, Mundang 2.7%, Bidiyo/Migaama/Kenga/Dangleat
2.5%, Dadjo/Kibet/Muro 2.4%, Tupuri/Kera 2%,
Gabri/Kabalaye/Nanchere/Somrai 2%, Fulani/Fulbe/Bodore 1.8%,
Karo/Zime/Peve 1.3%, Baguirmi/Barma 1.2%, Zaghawa/Bideyat/Kobe
1.1%, Tama/Assongori/Mararit 1.1%, Mesmedje/Massalat/Kadjakse 0.8%,
other Chadian ethnicities 3.4%, Chadians of foreign ethnicities
0.9%, foreign nationals 0.3%, unspecified 1.7% (2014-15 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Languages">French (official), Arabic (official), Sara (in south), more than
120 different languages and dialects<br/>
         <br/>
major-language sample(s):<br/>
The World Factbook, une source indispensable d'informations de
base. (French)<br/>
         <br/>
كتاب حقائق العالم، المصدر الذي لا يمكن الاستغناء عنه للمعلومات
الأساسية (Arabic)<br/>
         <br/>
The World Factbook, the indispensable source for basic
information.</subsection>
      <subsection title="Religions">Muslim 52.1%, Protestant 23.9%, Roman Catholic 20%, animist
0.3%, other Christian 0.2%, none 2.8%, unspecified 0.7% (2014-15
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Demographic profile">Despite the start of oil production in 2003, around 40% of
Chad’s population lived below the poverty line as of 2018. The
population will continue to grow rapidly because of the country’s
very high fertility rate and large youth cohort – more than 65% of
the populace is under the age of 25 as of 2022 – although the
mortality rate is high and life expectancy is low. Chad has the
world’s second highest maternal mortality rate as of 2017. Among
the primary risk factors are poverty, anemia, rural habitation,
high fertility, poor education, and a lack of access to family
planning and obstetric care. Impoverished, uneducated adolescents
living in rural areas are most affected. To improve women’s
reproductive health and reduce fertility, Chad will need to
increase women’s educational attainment, job participation, and
knowledge of and access to family planning. Less than a quarter of
women are literate, less than 10% use contraceptives, and more than
40% undergo genital cutting.As of December 2022, more than 403,000 refugees from Sudan and
more than 120,000 from the Central African Republic strain Chad’s
limited resources and create tensions in host communities.
Thousands of new refugees fled to Chad in 2013 to escape worsening
violence in the Darfur region of Sudan. The large refugee
populations are hesitant to return to their home countries because
of continued instability. Chad was relatively stable in 2012 in
comparison to other states in the region, but past fighting between
government forces and opposition groups and inter-communal violence
have left more than 380,000 of its citizens displaced in the
eastern part of the country as of 2022.</subsection>
      <subsection title="Age structure">0-14 years: 47.43% (male 4,050,505/female
3,954,413)<br/>
         <br/>
15-24 years: 19.77% (male 1,676,495/female
1,660,417)<br/>
         <br/>
25-54 years: 27.14% (male 2,208,181/female
2,371,490)<br/>
         <br/>
55-64 years: 3.24% (male 239,634/female
306,477)<br/>
         <br/>
65 years and over: 2.43% (male 176,658/female
233,087) (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Dependency ratios">total dependency ratio: 98.7<br/>
         <br/>
youth dependency ratio: 94.7<br/>
         <br/>
elderly dependency ratio: 4<br/>
         <br/>
potential support ratio: 24.9 (2021 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Median age">total: 16.1 years<br/>
         <br/>
male: 15.6 years<br/>
         <br/>
female: 16.5 years (2020 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 223</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population growth rate">3.09% (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 10</subsection>
      <subsection title="Birth rate">40.45 births/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 6</subsection>
      <subsection title="Death rate">9.45 deaths/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 49</subsection>
      <subsection title="Net migration rate">-0.13 migrant(s)/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 105</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">the population is unevenly distributed due to contrasts in
climate and physical geography; the highest density is found in the
southwest, particularly around Lake Chad and points south; the dry
Saharan zone to the north is the least densely populated as shown
in this <br/>population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">urban population: 24.4% of total population
(2023)<br/>
         <br/>
rate of urbanization: 4.1% annual rate of change
(2020-25 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major urban areas - population">1.592 million N'DJAMENA (capital) (2023)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sex ratio">at birth: 1.04 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
0-14 years: 1.02 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
15-24 years: 1.01 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
25-54 years: 0.92 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
55-64 years: 0.77 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
65 years and over: 0.69 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
total population: 0.98 male(s)/female (2022
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Mother's mean age at first birth">18.1 years (2014/15 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: data represents median age at first birth
among women 20-49</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maternal mortality ratio">1,140 deaths/100,000 live births (2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 2</subsection>
      <subsection title="Infant mortality rate">total: 65.48 deaths/1,000 live births<br/>
         <br/>
male: 71.21 deaths/1,000 live births<br/>
         <br/>
female: 59.52 deaths/1,000 live births (2022
est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 7</subsection>
      <subsection title="Life expectancy at birth">total population: 59.15 years<br/>
         <br/>
male: 57.32 years<br/>
         <br/>
female: 61.06 years (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 222</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total fertility rate">5.46 children born/woman (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 5</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gross reproduction rate">2.62 (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Contraceptive prevalence rate">8.1% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Drinking water source">improved: urban: 90.2% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 51.9% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 60.9% of population<br/>
         <br/>
unimproved: urban: 9.8% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 48.1% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 39.1% of population (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Current health expenditure">5.4% of GDP (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Physicians density">0.06 physicians/1,000 population (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sanitation facility access">improved: urban: 57.5% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 4.9% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 17.3% of population<br/>
         <br/>
unimproved: urban: 42.5% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 95.1% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 82.7% of population (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="HIV/AIDS - adult prevalence rate">1.1% (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 36</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">degree of risk: very high (2020)<br/>
         <br/>
food or waterborne diseases: bacterial and
protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever<br/>
         <br/>
vectorborne diseases: malaria and dengue
fever<br/>
         <br/>
water contact diseases: schistosomiasis<br/>
         <br/>
animal contact diseases: rabies<br/>
         <br/>
respiratory diseases: meningococcal
meningitis<br/>
         <br/>
note: on 21 March 2022, the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a Travel Alert for polio in
Africa; Chad is currently considered a high risk to travelers for
circulating vaccine-derived polioviruses (cVDPV); vaccine-derived
poliovirus (VDPV) is a strain of the weakened poliovirus that was
initially included in oral polio vaccine (OPV) and that has
changed over time and behaves more like the wild or naturally
occurring virus; this means it can be spread more easily to
people who are unvaccinated against polio and who come in contact
with the stool or respiratory secretions, such as from a sneeze, of
an “infected” person who received oral polio vaccine; the CDC
recommends that before any international travel, anyone
unvaccinated, incompletely vaccinated, or with an unknown polio
vaccination status should complete the routine polio vaccine
series; before travel to any high-risk destination, the CDC
recommends that adults who previously completed the full, routine
polio vaccine series receive a single, lifetime booster dose of
polio vaccine</subsection>
      <subsection title="Obesity - adult prevalence rate">6.1% (2016)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 170</subsection>
      <subsection title="Alcohol consumption per capita">total: 0.55 liters of pure alcohol (2019
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
beer: 0.37 liters of pure alcohol (2019
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
wine: 0.01 liters of pure alcohol (2019
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
spirits: 0.01 liters of pure alcohol (2019
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
other alcohols: 0.16 liters of pure alcohol (2019
est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 162</subsection>
      <subsection title="Tobacco use">total: 8.3% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
male: 13.8% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
female: 2.7% (2020 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 146</subsection>
      <subsection title="Children under the age of 5 years underweight">29.2% (2019)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 7</subsection>
      <subsection title="Currently married women (ages 15-49)">70.6% (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Child marriage">women married by age 15: 24.2%<br/>
         <br/>
women married by age 18: 60.6%<br/>
         <br/>
men married by age 18: 8.1% (2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Education expenditures">2.9% of GDP (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 162</subsection>
      <subsection title="Literacy">definition: age 15 and over can read and write
French or Arabic<br/>
         <br/>
total population: 22.3%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 31.3%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 14% (2016)</subsection>
      <subsection title="School life expectancy (primary to tertiary education)">total: 7 years<br/>
         <br/>
male: 9 years<br/>
         <br/>
female: 6 years (2015)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">total: 2.4%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 3.3%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 1.4% (2021 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Environment">
      <subsection title="Environment - current issues">inadequate supplies of potable water; improper waste disposal in
rural areas and poor farming practices contribute to soil and water
pollution; desertification</subsection>
      <subsection title="Environment - international agreements">party to: Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate
Change-Kyoto Protocol, Climate Change-Paris Agreement,
Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban, Desertification, Endangered
Species, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Nuclear Test Ban, Ozone
Layer Protection, Wetlands<br/>
         <br/>
signed, but not ratified: Marine Dumping-London
Convention</subsection>
      <subsection title="Air pollutants">particulate matter emissions: 53.01 micrograms
per cubic meter (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
carbon dioxide emissions: 1.02 megatons (2016
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
methane emissions: 30.69 megatons (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">tropical in south, desert in north</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">agricultural land: 39.6% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
arable land: 3.9% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent crops: 0% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent pasture: 35.7% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
forest: 9.1% (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
other: 51.3% (2018 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">urban population: 24.4% of total population
(2023)<br/>
         <br/>
rate of urbanization: 4.1% annual rate of change
(2020-25 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Revenue from forest resources">forest revenues: 3.81% of GDP (2018 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 19</subsection>
      <subsection title="Revenue from coal">coal revenues: 0% of GDP (2018 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 78</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">degree of risk: very high (2020)<br/>
         <br/>
food or waterborne diseases: bacterial and
protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever<br/>
         <br/>
vectorborne diseases: malaria and dengue
fever<br/>
         <br/>
water contact diseases: schistosomiasis<br/>
         <br/>
animal contact diseases: rabies<br/>
         <br/>
respiratory diseases: meningococcal
meningitis<br/>
         <br/>
note: on 21 March 2022, the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a Travel Alert for polio in
Africa; Chad is currently considered a high risk to travelers for
circulating vaccine-derived polioviruses (cVDPV); vaccine-derived
poliovirus (VDPV) is a strain of the weakened poliovirus that was
initially included in oral polio vaccine (OPV) and that has
changed over time and behaves more like the wild or naturally
occurring virus; this means it can be spread more easily to
people who are unvaccinated against polio and who come in contact
with the stool or respiratory secretions, such as from a sneeze, of
an “infected” person who received oral polio vaccine; the CDC
recommends that before any international travel, anyone
unvaccinated, incompletely vaccinated, or with an unknown polio
vaccination status should complete the routine polio vaccine
series; before travel to any high-risk destination, the CDC
recommends that adults who previously completed the full, routine
polio vaccine series receive a single, lifetime booster dose of
polio vaccine</subsection>
      <subsection title="Food insecurity">widespread lack of access: due to civil
insecurity and shortfall in cereal production - according to
the latest analysis, about 2.1 million people are projected to be
in "Crisis" and above, between June and August 2022 due to
persisting insecurity in Lac and Tibesti regions that disrupted
livelihood activities and caused population displacements, as well
as a below-average cereal production in 2021; as of September 2022,
floods destroyed about 45,000 hectares of crops and affected more
than 450,000 people, mostly in the provinces of Logone Occidental,
Mandoul and Sila, increasing the risk of a deterioration of food
insecurity (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waste and recycling">municipal solid waste generated annually:
1,358,851 tons (2010 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major lakes (area sq km)">fresh water lake(s): Lake Chad (endorheic lake
shared with Niger, Nigeria, and Cameroon) - 10,360-25,900 sq
km<br/>
note - area varies by season and year to year</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Niger (2,261,741 sq km)<br/>
Internal (endorheic basin) drainage: Lake Chad (2,497,738
sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major aquifers">Lake Chad Basin, Nubian Aquifer System</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total water withdrawal">municipal: 103.7 million cubic meters (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
industrial: 103.7 million cubic meters (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
agricultural: 672.2 million cubic meters (2017
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total renewable water resources">45.7 billion cubic meters (2019 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Government">
      <subsection title="Country name">conventional long form: Republic of Chad<br/>
         <br/>
conventional short form: Chad<br/>
         <br/>
local long form: Republique du Tchad/Jumhuriyat
Tshad<br/>
         <br/>
local short form: Tchad/Tshad<br/>
         <br/>
etymology: named for Lake Chad, which lies along
the country's western border; the word "tsade" means "large body of
water" or "lake" in several local native languages<br/>
         <br/>
note: the only country whose name is composed of a
single syllable with a single vowel</subsection>
      <subsection title="Government type">presidential republic</subsection>
      <subsection title="Capital">name: N'Djamena<br/>
         <br/>
geographic coordinates: 12 06 N, 15 02 E<br/>
         <br/>
time difference: UTC+1 (6 hours ahead of
Washington, DC, during Standard Time)<br/>
         <br/>
etymology: name taken from the Arab name of a
nearby village, Nijamina, meaning "place of rest"</subsection>
      <subsection title="Administrative divisions">23 provinces (provinces, singular - province); Barh-El-Gazel,
Batha, Borkou, Chari-Baguirmi, Ennedi-Est, Ennedi-Ouest, Guera,
Hadjer-Lamis, Kanem, Lac, Logone Occidental, Logone Oriental,
Mandoul, Mayo-Kebbi-Est, Mayo-Kebbi-Ouest, Moyen-Chari, N'Djamena,
Ouaddai, Salamat, Sila, Tandjile, Tibesti, Wadi-Fira</subsection>
      <subsection title="Independence">11 August 1960 (from France)</subsection>
      <subsection title="National holiday">Independence Day, 11 August (1960)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Constitution">history: several previous; latest approved 30
April 2018 by the National Assembly, entered into force 4 May 2018;
suspended 21 April 2021 and remained so through April 2022<br/>
         <br/>
amendments: proposed as a revision by the
president of the republic after a Council of Ministers (cabinet)
decision or by the National Assembly; approval for consideration of
a revision requires at least three-fifths majority vote by the
Assembly; passage requires approval by referendum or at least
two-thirds majority vote by the Assembly</subsection>
      <subsection title="Legal system">mixed legal system of civil and customary law</subsection>
      <subsection title="International law organization participation">has not submitted an ICJ jurisdiction declaration; accepts ICCt
jurisdiction</subsection>
      <subsection title="Citizenship">citizenship by birth: no<br/>
         <br/>
citizenship by descent only: both parents must be
citizens of Chad<br/>
         <br/>
dual citizenship recognized: Chadian law does not
address dual citizenship<br/>
         <br/>
residency requirement for naturalization: 15
years</subsection>
      <subsection title="Suffrage">18 years of age; universal</subsection>
      <subsection title="Executive branch">chief of state: Interim President Mahamat
Idriss DEBY (since 20 April 2021); note - on 20 April 2021, newly
reelected President Idriss DEBY Itno, Lt. Gen. died of injuries he
sustained following clashes between government forces he was
commanding and insurgents in the northern part of the country;
following his death, Mahamat Idriss DEBY took control of the
country and dismissed the Chadian parliament, establishing a
Transitional Military Council and promising elections within
eighteen months<br/>
         <br/>
head of government: Interim Prime Minister Albert
Pahimi PADACKE (since 26 April 2021); note - PADACKE was appointed
interim prime minister by the Transitional Military Council led by
Mahamat Idriss DEBY<br/>
         <br/>
cabinet: Council of Ministers<br/>
         <br/>
elections/appointments: president directly elected
by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for a
5-year term (no term limits); election last held on 11 April 2021;
note - on 20 April 2021, military officials suspended the
Constitution and formed a Transitional Military Council, pledging
to hold democratic elections in October 2022<br/>
         <br/>
election results: 2021: Lt. Gen. Idriss
DEBY Itno reelected; percent of vote - Lt. Gen. Idriss DEBY (MPS)
79.3%, Pahimi PADACKET Albert (RNDT) 10.3%, Lydie BEASSEMDA (Party
for Democracy and Independence) 3.2%, other 7.2%<br/>
         <br/>
2016: Lt. Gen. Idriss DEBY Itno reelected president in
first round; percent of vote - Lt. Gen. Idriss DEBY (MPS) 61.6%,
Saleh KEBZABO (UNDR) 12.8%, Laokein Kourayo MEDAR (CTPD) 10.7%,
Djimrangar DADNADJI (CAP-SUR) 5.1%, other 9.8%</subsection>
      <subsection title="Legislative branch">description: formerly a unicameral National
Assembly or Assemblée Nationale (188 seats; 163 directly
elected in multi-seat constituencies by proportional representation
vote and 25 directly elected in single-seat constituencies by
absolute majority vote with a second round if needed; members serve
4-year terms); note - on 5 October 2021, Interim President Mahamat
Idriss DEBY installed 93 members of an interim parliament, called
the National Transitional Council (NTC), replacing the National
Assembly which was disbanded after he took control of the country
on 20 April 2021; according to DEBY, the NTC will act as a national
assembly of transition until the country’s next elections take
place<br/>
         <br/>
elections: members of the so called "National
Transitional Council" were installed by Interim President DEBY on 5
October 2021 (next parliamentary elections to be held September
2022)<br/>
         <br/>
election results: percent of vote by party - NA;
seats by party - NA; composition - men 64, women 29, percent of
women 31.2%<br/>
         <br/>
note: the National Assembly mandate was extended
to 2020, reportedly due to a lack of funding for the scheduled 2015
election; the MPS has held a majority in the NA since 1997</subsection>
      <subsection title="Judicial branch">highest court(s): Supreme Court (consists of
the chief justice, 3 chamber presidents, and 12 judges or
councilors and divided into 3 chambers); Constitutional Council
(consists of 3 judges and 6 jurists)<br/>
         <br/>
judge selection and term of office: Supreme Court
chief justice selected by the president; councilors - 8 designated
by the president and 7 by the speaker of the National Assembly;
chief justice and councilors appointed for life; Constitutional
Council judges - 2 appointed by the president and 1 by the speaker
of the National Assembly; jurists - 3 each by the president and by
the speaker of the National Assembly; judges appointed for 9-year
terms<br/>
         <br/>
subordinate courts: High Court of Justice; Courts
of Appeal; tribunals; justices of the peace</subsection>
      <subsection title="Political parties and leaders">Chadian Convention for Peace and Development or CTPD [Laoukein
Kourayo MEDARD]<br/>
Federation Action for the Republic or FAR [Ngarledjy
YORONGAR]<br/>
National Rally for Development and Progress or Viva-RNDP [Dr.
Nouradine Delwa Kassire COUMAKOYE]<br/>
National Union for Democracy and Renewal or UNDR [Saleh
KEBZABO]<br/>
Party for Unity and Reconstruction or PUR<br/>
Patriotic Salvation Movement or MPS [formerly Idriss
DEBY] <br/>
Rally for Democracy and Progress or RDP [Mahamat Allahou
TAHER]<br/>
Rally of Chadian Nationalists/Awakening or RNDT/Le Reveil [Albert
Pahimi PADACKE]<br/>
Social Democratic Party for a Change-over of Power or PDSA [Malloum
YOBODA]<br/>
Union for Democracy and the Republic or UDR<br/>
Union for Renewal and Democracy or URD [Felix Romadoumngar
NIALBE]<br/>
 <br/>
note 1: 19 additional parties each contributed one
member<br/>
note 2: only parties with at least two seats in the last
elected National Assembly (February 2011) included<br/>
         <br/>
note: on 5 October 2021, Interim President Mahamat
Idriss DEBY appointed 93 members to the interim National
Transitional Council (NTC); 30% of the NTC members were retained
from parties previously represented in the National Assembly</subsection>
      <subsection title="International organization participation">ACP, AfDB, AU, BDEAC, CEMAC, EITI (compliant country), FAO, FZ,
G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS,
ILO, IMF, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), LCBC,
MIGA, MINUSMA, MNJTF, NAM, OIC, OIF, OPCW, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO,
UNIDO, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation in the US">chief of mission: Ambassador Koutou NGOTE GALI
(since 22 June 2018)<br/>
         <br/>
chancery: 2401 Massachusetts Avenue NW,
Washington, DC 20008<br/>
         <br/>
telephone: [1] (202) 652-1312<br/>
         <br/>
FAX: [1] (202) 265-1937<br/>
         <br/>
email address and website:<br/>
info@chadembassy.us<br/>
         <br/>
         <br/>https://chadembassy.us/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation from the US">chief of mission: Ambassador (vacant); Charge
d'Affaires Ellen THORBURN (since 8 November 2021)<br/>
         <br/>
embassy: Rond-Point Chagoua, B.P. 413,
N’Djamena<br/>
         <br/>
mailing address: 2410 N'Djamena Place, Washington
DC  20521-2410<br/>
         <br/>
telephone: [235] 2251-5017<br/>
         <br/>
FAX: [235] 2253-9102<br/>
         <br/>
email address and website:<br/>
NdjamenaACS@state.gov<br/>
         <br/>
         <br/>https://td.usembassy.gov/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Flag description">three equal vertical bands of blue (hoist side), gold, and red;
the flag combines the blue and red French (former colonial) colors
with the red and yellow (gold) of the Pan-African colors; blue
symbolizes the sky, hope, and the south of the country, which is
relatively well-watered; gold represents the sun, as well as the
desert in the north of the country; red stands for progress, unity,
and sacrifice<br/>
         <br/>
note: almost identical to the flag of Romania but
with a darker shade of blue; also similar to the flags of Andorra
and Moldova, both of which have a national coat of arms centered in
the yellow band; design based on the flag of France</subsection>
      <subsection title="National symbol(s)">goat (north), lion (south); national colors: blue, yellow,
red</subsection>
      <subsection title="National anthem">name: "La Tchadienne" (The Chadian)<br/>
         <br/>
lyrics/music: Louis GIDROL and his students/Paul
VILLARD<br/>
         <br/>
note: adopted 1960</subsection>
      <subsection title="National heritage">total World Heritage Sites: 2 (1 natural, 1
mixed)<br/>
         <br/>
selected World Heritage Site locales: Lakes of
Ounianga (n); Ennedi Massif: Natural and Cultural Landscape (m)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Economy">
      <subsection title="Economic overview">primarily oil-based economy, vulnerable to regional competition
and international price shocks; increasing extreme poverty and
minimal human capital capacities; one of the most environmentally
disrupted economies; high maternal and infant mortality rates
destabilizing labor force potentials</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP (purchasing power parity)">$24.49 billion (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$24.787 billion (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$25.19 billion (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: data are in 2017 dollars<br/>country
comparison to the world: 147</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP growth rate">-1.2% (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-1.6% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
3.25% (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 200</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP per capita">$1,400 (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$1,500 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$1,600 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: data are in 2017 dollars<br/>country
comparison to the world: 222</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP (official exchange rate)">$10.912 billion (2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Inflation rate (consumer prices)">-0.77% (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
4.46% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-0.97% (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 4</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by sector of origin">agriculture: 52.3% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
industry: 14.7% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
services: 33.1% (2017 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by end use">household consumption: 75.1% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
government consumption: 4.4% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
investment in fixed capital: 24.1% (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
investment in inventories: 0.7% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports of goods and services: 35.1% (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports of goods and services: -39.4% (2017
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Agricultural products">sorghum, groundnuts, millet, yams, cereals, sugar cane, beef,
maize, cotton, cassava</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industries">oil, cotton textiles, brewing, natron (sodium carbonate), soap,
cigarettes, construction materials</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industrial production growth rate">0.3% (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 156</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force">5.246 million (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 79</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force - by occupation">agriculture: 80%<br/>
         <br/>
industry: 20% (2006 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Unemployment rate">1.88% (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
1.74% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
1.12% (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
NA<br/>country
comparison to the world: 16</subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">total: 2.4%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 3.3%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 1.4% (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 199</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population below poverty line">42.3% (2018 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gini Index coefficient - distribution of family income">37.5 (2018 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 78</subsection>
      <subsection title="Household income or consumption by percentage share">lowest 10%: 2.6%<br/>
         <br/>
highest 10%: 30.8% (2003)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget">revenues: $1.337 billion (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
expenditures: $1.481 billion (2017 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget surplus (+) or deficit (-)">-1.5% (of GDP) (2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 89</subsection>
      <subsection title="Public debt">52.5% of GDP (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
52.4% of GDP (2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 99</subsection>
      <subsection title="Taxes and other revenues">13.5% (of GDP) (2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 164</subsection>
      <subsection title="Fiscal year">calendar year</subsection>
      <subsection title="Current account balance">-$558 million (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-$926 million (2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 120</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports">$2.464 billion (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$2.187 billion (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: Data are in current year dollars and do not
include illicit exports or re-exports.<br/>country
comparison to the world: 153</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - partners">China 32%, United Arab Emirates 21%, India 19%, United States
10%, France 6%, Germany 5% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - commodities">crude petroleum, gold, livestock, sesame seeds, gum arabic,
insect resins (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports">$2.16 billion (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$1.997 billion (2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 173</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - partners">China 29%, United Arab Emirates 16%, France 10%, United States
8%, India 5% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - commodities">delivery trucks, paints, packaged medicines, aircraft,
broadcasting equipment (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Reserves of foreign exchange and gold">$310.032 million (31 December 2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$147.75 million (31 December 2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$8.575 million (31 December 2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 180</subsection>
      <subsection title="Debt - external">$1.724 billion (31 December 2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$1.281 billion (31 December 2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 154</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exchange rates">Cooperation Financiere en Afrique Centrale francs (XAF) per US
dollar -<br/>
         <br/>
554.531 (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
575.586 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
585.911 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
555.446 (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
580.657 (2017 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Energy">
      <subsection title="Electricity access">electrification - total population: 9%
(2019)<br/>
         <br/>
electrification - urban areas: 32% (2019)<br/>
         <br/>
electrification - rural areas: 1% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity">installed generating capacity: 87,000 kW (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 188.46 million kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
transmission/distribution losses: 111 million kWh
(2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity generation sources">fossil fuels: 96.8% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
nuclear: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
solar: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
wind: 3.2% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
hydroelectricity: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
tide and wave: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
geothermal: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
biomass and waste: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Coal">production: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
proven reserves: 0 metric tons (2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Petroleum">total petroleum production: 87,900 bbl/day
(2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
refined petroleum consumption: 12,600 bbl/day
(2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
crude oil and lease condensate exports: 116,000
bbl/day (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
crude oil and lease condensate imports: 0 bbl/day
(2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
crude oil estimated reserves: 1.5 billion barrels
(2021 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - production">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 130</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - exports">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 143</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - imports">2,285 bbl/day (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 189</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural gas">production: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
proven reserves: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Carbon dioxide emissions">1.771 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from coal and metallurgical coke: 0 metric tonnes
of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from petroleum and other liquids: 1.771 million
metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from consumed natural gas: 0 metric tonnes of CO2
(2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 162</subsection>
      <subsection title="Energy consumption per capita">1.575 million Btu/person (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 190</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Communications">
      <subsection title="Telephones - fixed lines">total subscriptions: 5,340 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
subscriptions per 100 inhabitants: (2020 est.)
less than 1<br/>country
comparison to the world: 204</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telephones - mobile cellular">total subscriptions: 8,687,151 (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
subscriptions per 100 inhabitants: 53 (2020
est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 95</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telecommunication systems">general assessment: the telecom infrastructure
is particularly poor; fixed, mobile and internet is well below
African averages; Chad’s telecom market offers some potential for
investors to develop services given the low starting base; the
country’s first 3G/LTE mobile license was awarded in April 2014;
Chad finally gained access to international fiber bandwidth in 2012
its national backbone infrastructure remains underdeveloped; the
World Bank-funded Central African Backbone (CAB) project takes in
Chad, while the country is also party to a Trans-Saharan Backbone
project which will link a fiber cable to Nigeria and Algeria
(2022)<br/>
         <br/>
domestic: fixed-line connections less than 1 per
100 persons; mobile-cellular subscribership base of about 53 per
100 persons (2020)<br/>
         <br/>
international: country code - 235; satellite earth
station - 1 Intelsat (Atlantic Ocean)<br/>
         <br/>
note: the COVID-19 pandemic continues to have a
significant impact on production and supply chains globally; since
2020, some aspects of the telecom sector have experienced a
downturn, particularly in mobile device production; progress toward
5G implementation has resumed, as well as upgrades to
infrastructure; consumer spending on telecom services has increased
due to the surge in demand for capacity and bandwidth; the crucial
nature of telecom services as a tool for work and school from home
is still evident, and the spike in this area has seen growth
opportunities for development of new tools and increased
services</subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadcast media">1 state-owned TV station; 2 privately-owned TV stations;
state-owned radio network, Radiodiffusion Nationale Tchadienne
(RNT), operates national and regional stations; over 10 private
radio stations; some stations rebroadcast programs from
international broadcasters (2017)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet country code">.td</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet users">total: 1,642,586 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
percent of population: 10% (2020 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 133</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transportation">
      <subsection title="National air transport system">number of registered air carriers: 2
(2020)<br/>
         <br/>
inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
carriers: 3</subsection>
      <subsection title="Civil aircraft registration country code prefix">TT</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports">total: 59 (2021)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 81</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with paved runways">total: 9<br/>
         <br/>
over 3,047 m: 2<br/>
         <br/>
2,438 to 3,047 m: 4<br/>
         <br/>
1,524 to 2,437 m: 2<br/>
         <br/>
under 914 m: 1 (2021)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with unpaved runways">total: 50<br/>
         <br/>
over 3,047 m: 1<br/>
         <br/>
2,438 to 3,047 m: 2<br/>
         <br/>
1,524 to 2,437 m: 14<br/>
         <br/>
914 to 1,523 m: 22<br/>
         <br/>
under 914 m: 11 (2021)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Pipelines">582 km oil (2013)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Roadways">total: 40,000 km (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
note: consists of 25,000 km of national and
regional roads and 15,000 km of local roads; 206 km of urban roads
are paved<br/>country
comparison to the world: 88</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waterways">12,400 km (2022) (Chari and Logone Rivers are navigable only in
wet season) Chari is 11,400 km Legone is 1,000 km<br/>country
comparison to the world: 12</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Military and Security">
      <subsection title="Military and security forces">Chadian National Army (Armee Nationale du Tchad, ANT): Ground
Forces (l'Armee de Terre, AdT), Chadian Air Force (l'Armee de l'Air
Tchadienne, AAT), General Direction of the Security Services of
State Institutions (Direction Generale des Services de Securite des
Institutions de l'Etat, GDSSIE); National Gendarmerie; Ministry of
Public Security and Immigration: National Nomadic Guard of Chad
(GNNT), Chadian National Police (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
note: the GDSSIE, formerly known as the Republican
Guard, is the presidential guard force and is considered to be
Chad's elite military unit; it is reportedly a division-size unit
with infantry, armor, and special forces/anti-terrorism regiments
(known as the Special Anti-Terrorist Group or SATG, aka Division of
Special Anti-Terrorist Groups or DGSAT)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military expenditures">2.5% of GDP (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
2.9% of GDP (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
2% of GDP (2019 est.) (approximately $320 million)<br/>
         <br/>
2% of GDP (2018 est.) (approximately $310 million)<br/>
         <br/>
2% of GDP (2017 est.) (approximately $310 million)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 39</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military and security service personnel strengths">limited and varied information; estimated to have up to 35,000
active ANT personnel (25-30,000 Ground Forces; 300 Air Force;
approximately 5,000 GDSSIE); approximately 5,000 National
Gendarmerie; approximately 3,000 Nomadic Guard (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military equipment inventories and acquisitions">the ANT is mostly armed with older or secondhand equipment from
Belgium, France, Russia, and the former Soviet Union; in recent
years it has received equipment, including donations, from other
countries, including China, Italy, Ukraine, and the US   
(2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military service age and obligation">20 is the legal minimum age for compulsory military service for
men with an 18-36 month service obligation (information varies);
women are subject to 12 months of compulsory military or civic
service at age 21; 18-35 for voluntary service; soldiers released
from active duty are in the reserves until the age of 50 (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military deployments">1,450 Mali (MINUSMA) (May 2022)<br/>
         <br/>
note 1: Chad has committed approximately
1,000-1,500 troops to the Multinational Joint Task Force (MNJTF)
against Boko Haram and other terrorist groups operating in the
general area of the Lake Chad Basin and along Nigeria's northeast
border; national MNJTF troop contingents are deployed within their
own territories, although cross‐border operations are conducted
periodically; in 2019, Chad sent more than 1,000 troops to
Nigeria’s Borno State to fight Boko Haram as part of the MNJTF
mission<br/>
         <br/>
note 2: Chad is also part of a four (formerly
five)-nation anti-jihadist task force known as the G4 Sahel Group,
set up in 2014 with Chad, Mali (withdrew in 2022), Mauritania, and
Niger; it has committed 550 troops and 100 gendarmes to the force;
as of 2020, defense forces from each of the participating states
were allowed to pursue terrorist fighters up to 100 km into
neighboring countries; the force is backed by France, the UN, and
the US</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military - note">as of 2022, the ANT was chiefly focused on counterterrorism and
counterinsurgency operations; it was engaged with the Boko Haram
(BH) and the Islamic State in West Africa (ISWA) terrorist groups
in the Lake Chad Basin area (primarily the Lac Province) and in the
Sahel, particularly the tri-border area with Burkina Faso, Mali,
and Niger; in addition, the ANT was conducting operations against
internal anti-government militias and armed dissident groups<br/>
         <br/>
several rebel groups operate in northern Chad from bases in
southern Libya, including the FACT (Front pour le Changement et la
Concorde au Tchad), the Military Command Council for the Salvation
of the Republic le Conseil de Commandement Militaire pour le salut
de la République or CCSMR), the Union of Forces for Democracy and
Development (le Union des Forces pour la Démocratie et le
Développement or UFDD), and the Union of Resistance Forces (le
Union des Forces de la Résistance UFR); former Chadian President
Idriss DEBY was killed in April 2021 during fighting in the
northern part of the country between the FACT and the Chadian Army;
some armed groups, including the UFDD and UFR, signed an accord in
August 2022 in return for the release of prisoners, amnesty, and an
end to hostilities between the Chadian Government and these armed
factions; however, other armed groups, including the FACT and
CCSMR, refused to join the accord (2022)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Terrorism">
      <subsection title="Terrorist group(s)">Boko Haram; Islamic State of Iraq and ash-Sham - West Africa
(ISIS-WA)<br/>
         <br/>
note: details about the history, aims, leadership,
organization, areas of operation, tactics, targets, weapons, size,
and sources of support of the group(s) appear(s) in <br/>Appendix-T</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transnational Issues">
      <subsection title="Disputes - international">since 2003, ad hoc armed militia groups and the Sudanese
military have driven hundreds of thousands of Darfur residents into
Chad; Chad wishes to be a helpful mediator in resolving the Darfur
conflict, and in 2010 established a joint border monitoring force
with Sudan, which has helped to reduce cross-border banditry and
violence; only Nigeria and Cameroon have heeded the Lake Chad
Commission's admonition to ratify the delimitation treaty, which
also includes the Chad-Niger and Niger-Nigeria boundaries</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refugees and internally displaced persons">refugees (country of origin): 403,846 (Sudan),
42,597 (Cameroon) (2022); 124,545 (Central African Republic),
20,498 (Nigeria) (2023)<br/>
         <br/>
IDPs: 381,289 (majority are in the east)
(2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Trafficking in persons">tier rating: Tier 2 Watch List — Chad does not
fully meet the minimum standards for the elimination of trafficking
but is making significant efforts to do so; officials investigated
trafficking cases and finalized a National Action Plan for
2021-2022 and began implementation of standard operating procedures
and a National Referral Mechanism for identifying and referring
victims for care; however, the government did not demonstrate
overall increased efforts to increase anti-trafficking capacity;
government turnover hindered Chad’s ability to maintain consistent
anti-trafficking efforts and reporting; authorities did not report
prosecuting or convicting any traffickers, identifying victims, or
conducting awareness campaigns; nonetheless, because the government
has devoted sufficient resources to a written plan that, if
implemented, would constitute significant efforts to meet the
minimum standards, Chad was granted a waiver per the TVPA from
downgrade to Tier 3; therefore, Chad remained on Tier 2 Watch List
for the third consecutive year (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
trafficking profile: human traffickers exploit
domestic and foreign victims in Chad, and traffickers exploit
Chadian victims abroad; most trafficking is internal; some children
are sent by their parents to relatives or intermediaries to receive
education, an apprenticeship, goods, or money and are then forced
to work in domestic service or cattle herding; children are also
forced to work in agriculture, gold mines, charcoal vending, and
fishing, and those attending Koranic schools are forced into
begging and street vending; girls from rural areas who search for
work in larger towns are exploited in sex trafficking and domestic
servitude; terrorist groups abduct children to serve as soldiers,
suicide bombers, brides, and forced laborers (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Illicit drugs">NA</subsection>
   </section>
</country>
