<country>
   <name>Saint Helena, Ascension, and Tristan da
Cunha</name>
   <section title="Photos of Saint Helena, Ascension, and Tristan da Cunha"/>
   <section title="Introduction">
      <subsection title="Background">Saint Helena is a British Overseas Territory consisting of Saint
Helena and Ascension Islands, and the island group of Tristan da
Cunha.<note title="Saint Helena">Uninhabited when first discovered by the Portuguese in 1502, Saint Helena was garrisoned by the British during the 17th century. It acquired fame as the place of Napoleon BONAPARTE's exile from 1815 until his death in 1821, but its importance as a port of call declined after the opening of the Suez Canal in 1869. During the Anglo-Boer War in South Africa, several thousand Boer prisoners were confined on the island between 1900 and 1903.</note>Saint Helena is one of the most remote populated places in the
world. The British Government committed to building an airport on
Saint Helena in 2005. After more than a decade of delays and
construction, a commercial air service to South Africa via Namibia
was inaugurated in October of 2017. The weekly service to Saint
Helena from Johannesburg via Windhoek in Namibia takes just over
six hours (including the refueling stop in Windhoek) and replaces
the mail ship that had made a five-day journey to the island every
three weeks.<note title="Ascension Island">This barren and uninhabited island was discovered and named by the Portuguese in 1503. The British garrisoned the island in 1815 to prevent a rescue of NAPOLEON from Saint Helena. It served as a provisioning station for the Royal Navy's West Africa Squadron on anti-slavery patrol. The island remained under Admiralty control until 1922, when it became a dependency of Saint Helena. During World War II, the UK permitted the US to construct an airfield on Ascension in support of transatlantic flights to Africa and anti-submarine operations in the South Atlantic. In the 1960s the island became an important space tracking station for the US. In 1982, Ascension was an essential staging area for British forces during the Falklands War. It remains a critical refueling point in the air-bridge from the UK to the South Atlantic.</note>The island hosts one of four dedicated ground antennas that
assist in the operation of the Global Positioning System (GPS)
navigation system (the others are on Diego Garcia (British Indian
Ocean Territory), Kwajalein (Marshall Islands), and at Cape
Canaveral, Florida (US)). NASA and the US Air Force also operate a
Meter-Class Autonomous Telescope (MCAT) on Ascension as part of the
deep space surveillance system for tracking orbital debris, which
can be a hazard to spacecraft and astronauts.<note title="Tristan da Cunha">The island group consists of Tristan da Cunha, Nightingale, Inaccessible, and Gough Islands. Tristan da Cunha, named after its Portuguese discoverer (1506), was garrisoned by the British in 1816 to prevent any attempt to rescue NAPOLEON from Saint Helena. Gough and Inaccessible Islands have been designated World Heritage Sites. South Africa leases a site for a meteorological station on Gough Island.</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Geography">
      <subsection title="Location">islands in the South Atlantic Ocean, about midway between South
America and Africa; Ascension Island lies 1,300 km (800 mi)
northwest of Saint Helena; Tristan da Cunha lies 4,300 km (2,700
mi) southwest of Saint Helena</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geographic coordinates">
         <note title="Saint Helena">15 57 S, 5 42 W;</note>
         <note title="Ascension Island">7 57 S, 14 22 W;</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha island group">37 15 S, 12 30 W</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Map references">Africa</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area">
         <note title="total">394 sq km</note>
         <note title="land">122 sq km Saint Helena Island</note>
         <note title="water">0 sq km</note>country
comparison to the world: 203</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area - comparative">slightly more than twice the size of Washington, DC</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land boundaries">
         <note title="total">0 km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Coastline">
         <note title="Saint Helena">60 km</note>
         <note title="Ascension Island">NA</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha (island only)">34 km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Maritime claims">
         <note title="territorial sea">12 nm</note>
         <note title="exclusive fishing zone">200 nm</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">
         <note title="Saint Helena">tropical marine; mild, tempered by trade winds;</note>
         <note title="Ascension Island">tropical marine; mild, semi-arid;</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha">temperate marine; mild, tempered by trade winds (tends to be cooler than Saint Helena)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Terrain">the islands of this group are of volcanic origin associated with
the Atlantic Mid-Ocean Ridge<note title="Saint Helena">rugged, volcanic; small scattered plateaus and plains;</note>
         <note title="Ascension">surface covered by lava flows and cinder cones of 44 dormant volcanoes; terrain rises to the east;</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha">sheer cliffs line the coastline of the nearly circular island; the flanks of the central volcanic peak are deeply dissected; narrow coastal plain lies between The Peak and the coastal cliffs</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Elevation">
         <note title="highest point">Queen Mary's Peak on Tristan da Cunha 2,060 m; Green Mountain on Ascension Island 859 m; Diana's Peak on Saint Helena Island 818 m</note>
         <note title="lowest point">Atlantic Ocean 0 m</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural resources">fish, lobster</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">
         <note title="agricultural land">30.8% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="forest">5.1% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="other">64.1% (2018 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Irrigated land">0 sq km (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">Saint Helena - population is concentrated in and around the
capital Jamestown in the northwest, with another significant
cluster in the interior Longwood area; Ascension - largest
settlement, and location of most of the population, is Georgetown;
Tristan da Cunha - most of the nearly 300 inhabitants live in the
northern coastal town of Edinburgh of the Seven Seas</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural hazards">active volcanism on Tristan da Cunha<note title="volcanism">the island volcanoes of Tristan da Cunha (2,060 m) and Nightingale Island (365 m) experience volcanic activity; Tristan da Cunha erupted in 1962 and Nightingale in 2004</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Geography - note">Saint Helena harbors at least 40 species of plants unknown
elsewhere in the world; Ascension is a breeding ground for sea
turtles and sooty terns; Queen Mary's Peak on Tristan da Cunha is
the highest island mountain in the South Atlantic and a prominent
landmark on the sea lanes around southern Africa</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="People and Society">
      <subsection title="Population">7,925 (2022 est.)
<note title="note">Saint Helena's Statistical Office estimated the resident population to be 4,439 in 2021; only Saint Helena, Ascension, and Tristan da Cunha islands are inhabited, none of the other nearby islands/islets are</note>country
comparison to the world: 224</subsection>
      <subsection title="Nationality">
         <note title="noun">Saint Helenian(s)</note>
         <note title="adjective">Saint Helenian</note>
         <note title="note">referred to locally as "Saints"</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Ethnic groups">African descent 50%, White 25%, Chinese 25%</subsection>
      <subsection title="Languages">English</subsection>
      <subsection title="Religions">Protestant 75.9% (includes Anglican 68.9, Baptist 2.1%, Seventh
Day Adventist 1.8%, Salvation Army 1.7%, New Apostolic 1.4%),
Jehovah's Witness 4.1%, Roman Catholic 1.2%, other 2.5% (includes
Baha'i), unspecified 0.8%, none 6.1%, no response 9.4% (2016
est.)
<note title="note">data represent Saint Helena only</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Demographic profile">The vast majority of the population of Saint Helena, Ascension,
and Tristan da Cunha live on Saint Helena. Ascension has no
indigenous or permanent residents and is inhabited only by persons
contracted to work on the island (mainly with the UK and US
military or in the space and communications industries) or their
dependents, while Tristan da Cunha – the main island in a small
archipelago – has fewer than 300 residents. The population of Saint
Helena consists of the descendants of 17th century British sailors
and settlers from the East India Company, African slaves, and
indentured servants and laborers from India, Indonesia, and China.
Most of the population of Ascension are Saint Helenians, Britons,
and Americans, while that of Tristan da Cunha descends from
shipwrecked sailors and Saint Helenians.Change in Saint Helena’s population size is driven by net
outward migration. Since the 1980s, Saint Helena’s population
steadily has shrunk and aged as the birth rate has decreased and
many working-age residents left for better opportunities elsewhere.
The restoration of British citizenship in 2002 accelerated family
emigration; from 1998 to 2008 alone, population declined by about
20%.In the 2010s, the population experienced some temporary growth,
as foreigners and returning Saint Helenians, came to build an
international airport, but numbers faded as the project reached
completion and workers departed. With the airport fully
operational, increased access to the remote island has the
potential to boost tourism and fishing, provide more jobs for Saint
Helenians domestically, and could encourage some ex-patriots to
return home. In the meantime, however, Saint Helena, Ascension, and
Tristan da Cunha have to contend with the needs of an aging
population. The elderly population of the islands has risen from an
estimated 9.4% in 1998 to 18% in 2022.</subsection>
      <subsection title="Age structure">
         <note title="0-14 years">14.66% (male 592/female 570)</note>
         <note title="15-24 years">11.7% (male 472/female 455)</note>
         <note title="25-54 years">42.59% (male 1,679/female 1,692)</note>
         <note title="55-64 years">13.53% (male 523/female 549)</note>
         <note title="65 years and over">18.06% (male 730/female 701) (2022 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Dependency ratios">
         <note title="total dependency ratio">68.6 NA</note>
         <note title="youth dependency ratio">23.6 NA</note>
         <note title="elderly dependency ratio">45.1 NA</note>
         <note title="potential support ratio">2.2 (2021) NA</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Median age">
         <note title="total">43.2 years</note>
         <note title="male">43.2 years</note>
         <note title="female">43.3 years (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 30</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population growth rate">0.13% (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 185</subsection>
      <subsection title="Birth rate">9.34 births/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 195</subsection>
      <subsection title="Death rate">8.08 deaths/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 86</subsection>
      <subsection title="Net migration rate">0 migrant(s)/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 96</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">Saint Helena - population is concentrated in and around the
capital Jamestown in the northwest, with another significant
cluster in the interior Longwood area; Ascension - largest
settlement, and location of most of the population, is Georgetown;
Tristan da Cunha - most of the nearly 300 inhabitants live in the
northern coastal town of Edinburgh of the Seven Seas</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">
         <note title="urban population">40.7% of total population (2023)</note>
         <note title="rate of urbanization">0.98% annual rate of change (2020-25 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major urban areas - population">1,000 JAMESTOWN (capital) (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sex ratio">
         <note title="at birth">1.06 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="0-14 years">1.04 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="15-24 years">1.04 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="25-54 years">1 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="55-64 years">0.96 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="65 years and over">0.81 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="total population">1.01 male(s)/female (2022 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Infant mortality rate">
         <note title="total">19.19 deaths/1,000 live births</note>
         <note title="male">23.05 deaths/1,000 live births</note>
         <note title="female">15.13 deaths/1,000 live births (2022 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 86</subsection>
      <subsection title="Life expectancy at birth">
         <note title="total population">80.48 years</note>
         <note title="male">77.58 years</note>
         <note title="female">83.51 years (2022 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 49</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total fertility rate">1.6 children born/woman (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 185</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gross reproduction rate">0.78 (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Contraceptive prevalence rate">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Drinking water source">
         <note title="improved">urban: NA</note>
         <note title="unimproved">urban: NA</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Current health expenditure">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Physicians density">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sanitation facility access">
         <note title="improved">urban: NA</note>
         <note title="unimproved">urban: NA</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="HIV/AIDS - adult prevalence rate">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Children under the age of 5 years underweight">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Education expenditures">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Literacy">
         <note title="total population">NA</note>
         <note title="male">NA</note>
         <note title="female">NA</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Environment">
      <subsection title="Environment - current issues">development threatens unique biota on Saint Helena</subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">
         <note title="Saint Helena">tropical marine; mild, tempered by trade winds;</note>
         <note title="Ascension Island">tropical marine; mild, semi-arid;</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha">temperate marine; mild, tempered by trade winds (tends to be cooler than Saint Helena)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">
         <note title="agricultural land">30.8% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="forest">5.1% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="other">64.1% (2018 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">
         <note title="urban population">40.7% of total population (2023)</note>
         <note title="rate of urbanization">0.98% annual rate of change (2020-25 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Government">
      <subsection title="Country name">
         <note title="conventional long form">Saint Helena, Ascension, and Tristan da Cunha</note>
         <note title="conventional short form">none</note>
         <note title="etymology">Saint Helena was discovered in 1502 by Galician navigator Joao da NOVA, sailing in the service of the Kingdom of Portugal, who named it "Santa Helena"; Ascension was named in 1503 by Portuguese navigator Afonso de ALBUQUERQUE who sighted the island on the Feast Day of the Ascension; Tristan da Cunha was discovered in 1506 by Portuguese explorer Tristao da CUNHA who christened the main island after himself (the name was subsequently anglicized)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Government type">parliamentary democracy</subsection>
      <subsection title="Dependency status">overseas territory of the UK</subsection>
      <subsection title="Capital">
         <note title="name">Jamestown</note>
         <note title="geographic coordinates">15 56 S, 5 43 W</note>
         <note title="time difference">UTC 0 (5 hours ahead of Washington, DC, during Standard Time)</note>
         <note title="etymology">founded in 1659 and named after James, Duke of York, who would become King JAMES II of England (r. 1785-1788)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Administrative divisions">3 administrative areas; Ascension, Saint Helena, Tristan da
Cunha</subsection>
      <subsection title="Independence">none (overseas territory of the UK)</subsection>
      <subsection title="National holiday">Official birthday of King Charles III, April or June as
designated by the governor</subsection>
      <subsection title="Constitution">
         <note title="history">several previous; latest effective 1 September 2009 (St Helena, Ascension and Tristan da Cunha Constitution Order 2009)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Legal system">English common law and local statutes</subsection>
      <subsection title="Citizenship">see United Kingdom</subsection>
      <subsection title="Suffrage">18 years of age</subsection>
      <subsection title="Executive branch">
         <note title="chief of state">King CHARLES III (since 8 September 2022)</note>
         <note title="head of government">Governor Nigel PHILLIPS (since 13 August 2022)</note>
         <note title="cabinet">Executive Council consists of the governor, 3 ex-officio officers, and 5 elected members of the Legislative Council</note>
         <note title="elections/appointments">none; the monarchy is hereditary; governor appointed by the monarch</note>
         <note title="note">the constitution order provides for an administrator for Ascension and Tristan da Cunha appointed by the governor</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Legislative branch">
         <note title="description">unicameral Legislative Council (17 seats including the speaker and deputy speaker; 12 members directly elected in a single countrywide constituency by simple majority vote and 3 ex-officio members - the chief secretary, financial secretary, and attorney general; members serve 4-year terms)</note>
         <note title="elections">last held on 13 October 2021 (next to be held in 2025)</note>
         <note title="election results">percent of vote - NA; seats by party - independent 12; composition - men 14, women 3, percent women 17.6%</note>
         <note title="note">the Constitution Order provides for separate Island Councils for both Ascension and Tristan da Cunha</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Judicial branch">
         <note title="highest court(s)">Court of Appeal (consists of the court president and 2 justices); Supreme Court (consists of the chief justice - a nonresident - and NA judges); note - appeals beyond the Court of Appeal are heard by the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council (in London)</note>
         <note title="judge selection and term of office">Court of Appeal and Supreme Court justices appointed by the governor acting upon the instructions from a secretary of state acting on behalf of King CHARLES III; justices of both courts serve until retirement at age 70, but terms can be extended</note>
         <note title="subordinate courts">Magistrates' Court; Small Claims Court; Juvenile Court</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Political parties and leaders">none</subsection>
      <subsection title="International organization participation">UPU</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation in the US">none (overseas territory of the UK)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation from the US">
         <note title="embassy">none (overseas territory of the UK)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Flag description">blue with the flag of the UK in the upper hoist-side quadrant
and the Saint Helenian shield centered on the outer half of the
flag; the upper third of the shield depicts a white plover (wire
bird) on a yellow field; the remainder of the shield depicts a
rocky coastline on the left, offshore is a three-masted sailing
ship with sails furled but flying an English flag</subsection>
      <subsection title="National symbol(s)">Saint Helena plover (bird)</subsection>
      <subsection title="National anthem">
         <note title="note">as an overseas territory of the UK, "God Save the King" is official (see United Kingdom)</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Economy">
      <subsection title="Economic overview">upper middle-income, British Atlantic Ocean territorial economy;
native (but pegged to British pound) currency user on 2 of 3
islands; significant UK financial support; unique land/farming
commune structure; military-related economic activity; sport
fishing locale</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP (purchasing power parity)">$31.1 million (2009 est.)country
comparison to the world: 227</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP growth rate">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP per capita">$7,800 (FY09/10 est.)country
comparison to the world: 156</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP (official exchange rate)">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Inflation rate (consumer prices)">4% (2012 est.)country
comparison to the world: 135</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by sector of origin">
         <note title="agriculture">NA</note>
         <note title="industry">NA</note>
         <note title="services">NA</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Agricultural products">coffee, corn, potatoes, vegetables; fish, lobster; livestock;
timber</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industries">construction, crafts (furniture, lacework, fancy woodwork),
fishing, collectible postage stamps</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industrial production growth rate">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force">2,486 (1998 est.)country
comparison to the world: 226</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force - by occupation">
         <note title="agriculture">6%</note>
         <note title="industry">48%</note>
         <note title="services">46% (1987 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Unemployment rate">14% (1998 est.)country
comparison to the world: 186</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population below poverty line">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Household income or consumption by percentage share">
         <note title="lowest 10%">NA</note>
         <note title="highest 10%">NA</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget">
         <note title="revenues">$8.427 million (FY06/07 est.)</note>
         <note title="expenditures">$20.7 million (FY06/07 est.)</note>
         <note title="note">revenue data reflect only locally raised revenues; the budget deficit is resolved by grant aid from the UK</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Fiscal year">1 April - 31 March</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports">$19 million (2004 est.)country
comparison to the world: 215</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - partners">United States 47%, Japan 12%, South Korea 10%, France 9%,
Australia 5% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - commodities">crustaceans, fish, integrated circuits, air conditioners,
clothing and apparel (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports">$20.53 million (2010 est.)country
comparison to the world: 223</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - partners">United Kingdom 65%, South Africa 21% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - commodities">refined petroleum, cranes, communion wafers, iron sheeting, cars
and vehicle parts (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Debt - external">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exchange rates">Saint Helenian pounds (SHP) per US dollar -

0.7836 (2017 est.)

0.6542 (2016 est.)

0.6542 (2015)

0.607 (2014 est.)

0.6391 (2013 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Energy">
      <subsection title="Electricity">
         <note title="installed generating capacity">8,000 kW (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">6.809 million kWh (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">0 kWh (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">0 kWh (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="transmission/distribution losses">1.688 million kWh (2019 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity generation sources">
         <note title="fossil fuels">100% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="nuclear">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="solar">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="wind">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="hydroelectricity">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="tide and wave">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="geothermal">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="biomass and waste">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Coal">
         <note title="production">0 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">0 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">0 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">0 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="proven reserves">0 metric tons (2019 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Petroleum">
         <note title="total petroleum production">0 bbl/day (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="refined petroleum consumption">100 bbl/day (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil and lease condensate exports">0 bbl/day (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil and lease condensate imports">0 bbl/day (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil estimated reserves">0 barrels (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - production">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 192</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - exports">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 193</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - imports">65 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 209</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural gas">
         <note title="production">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="proven reserves">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Carbon dioxide emissions">13,000 metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)
<note title="from coal and metallurgical coke">0 metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="from petroleum and other liquids">13,000 metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="from consumed natural gas">0 metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 215</subsection>
      <subsection title="Energy consumption per capita">0 Btu/person (2019 est.)country
comparison to the world: 208</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Communications">
      <subsection title="Telephones - fixed lines">
         <note title="total subscriptions">3,000 (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="subscriptions per 100 inhabitants">50 (2018 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 210</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telephones - mobile cellular">
         <note title="total subscriptions">4,000 (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="subscriptions per 100 inhabitants">67 (2019 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 222</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telecommunication systems">
         <note title="general assessment">capability to communicate worldwide; ADSL- broadband service; LTE coverage of 95% of population, includes voice calls, text messages, mobile data as well as inbound and outbound roaming; Wi-Fi hotspots in Jamestown, 1 ISP, many services are not offered locally but made available for visitors; some sun outages due to the reliance of international telephone and Internet communication relying on single satellite link (2020)</note>
         <note title="domestic">automatic digital network; fixed-line roughly 50 per 100 and mobile-cellular nearly 67 per 100 persons (2019)</note>
         <note title="international">country code (Saint Helena) - 290, (Ascension Island) - 247; landing point for the SaEx1 submarine cable providing connectivity to South Africa, Brazil, Virginia Beach (US) and islands in Saint Helena, Ascension and Tristan de Cunha; international direct dialing; satellite voice and data communications; satellite earth stations - 5 (Ascension Island - 4, Saint Helena - 1) (2019)</note>
         <note title="note">the COVID-19 pandemic continues to have a significant impact on production and supply chains globally; since 2020, some aspects of the telecom sector have experienced a downturn, particularly in mobile device production; progress toward 5G implementation has resumed, as well as upgrades to infrastructure; consumer spending on telecom services has increased due to the surge in demand for capacity and bandwidth; the crucial nature of telecom services as a tool for work and school from home is still evident, and the spike in this area has seen growth opportunities for development of new tools and increased services</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadcast media">Saint Helena has no local TV station; 2 local radio stations,
one of which is relayed to Ascension Island; satellite TV stations
rebroadcast terrestrially; Ascension Island has no local TV station
but has 1 local radio station and receives relays of broadcasts
from 1 radio station on Saint Helena; broadcasts from the British
Forces Broadcasting Service (BFBS) are available, as well as TV
services for the US military; Tristan da Cunha has 1 local radio
station and receives BFBS TV and radio broadcasts</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet country code">.sh; note - Ascension Island assigned .ac</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet users">
         <note title="total">2,302 (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="percent of population">38% (2019 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 225</subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadband - fixed subscriptions">
         <note title="total">1,000 (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="subscriptions per 100 inhabitants">17 (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 207</subsection>
      <subsection title="Communications - note">Ascension Island hosts one of four dedicated ground antennas
that assist in the operation of the Global Positioning System (GPS)
navigation system (the others are on Diego Garcia (British Indian
Ocean Territory), Kwajalein (Marshall Islands), and at Cape
Canaveral, Florida (US)); South Africa maintains a meteorological
station on Gough Island in the Tristan da Cunha archipelago</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transportation">
      <subsection title="Civil aircraft registration country code prefix">VQ-H</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports">
         <note title="total">2 (2021)</note>country
comparison to the world: 201</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with paved runways">
         <note title="total">2</note>
         <note title="over 3,047 m">1 Ascension Island - Wideawake Field (ASI)</note>
         <note title="1,524 to 2,437 m">1 (2021) Saint Helena (HLE);</note>
         <note title="note">weekly commercial air service to South Africa via Namibia commenced on 14 October 2017</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Roadways">
         <note title="total">198 km (2002) (Saint Helena 138 km, Ascension 40 km, Tristan da Cunha 20 km)</note>
         <note title="paved">168 km (2002) (Saint Helena 118 km, Ascension 40 km, Tristan da Cunha 10 km)</note>
         <note title="unpaved">30 km (2002) (Saint Helena 20 km, Tristan da Cunha 10 km)</note>country
comparison to the world: 208</subsection>
      <subsection title="Ports and terminals">
         <note title="major seaport(s)">Saint Helena</note>
         <note title="Saint Helena">Jamestown</note>
         <note title="Ascension Island">Georgetown</note>
         <note title="Tristan da Cunha">Calshot Harbor (Edinburgh)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Transportation - note">the new airport on Saint Helena opened for limited operations in
July 2016, and the first commercial flight took place on 14 October
2017, marking the start of weekly air service between Saint Helena
and South Africa via Namibia; the military airport on Ascension
Island is closed to civilian traffic; there is no air connection to
Tristan da Cunha and very limited sea connections making it one of
the most isolated communities on the planet</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Military and Security">
      <subsection title="Military - note">defense is the responsibility of the UK</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transnational Issues">
      <subsection title="Disputes - international">none identified</subsection>
   </section>
</country>
