<country>
   <name>South Sudan</name>
   <section title="Photos of South Sudan"/>
   <section title="Introduction">
      <subsection title="Background">South Sudan, which gained independence from Sudan on 9 July
2011, is the world’s newest country. Home to a diverse array of
mainly Nilotic ethnolinguistic groups that settled in the territory
in the 15th through 19th centuries, South Sudanese society is
heavily dependent on seasonal fluctuations in precipitation and
seasonal migration. The land comprising modern-day South Sudan was
conquered first by Egypt and later ruled jointly by
Egyptian-British colonial administrators in the late 19th century.
Christian missionaries propagated the spread of English and
Christianity, rather than Arabic and Islam, leading to significant
cultural differences between the northern and southern parts of
Sudan. When Sudan gained its independence in 1956, the Southern
region received assurances that it would participate fully in the
political system. However, the Arab government in Khartoum reneged
on its promises, prompting two periods of civil war (1955-1972 and
1983-2005) in which as many as 2.5 million people died - mostly
civilians - due largely to starvation and drought. The Second
Sudanese civil war was one of the deadliest since WWII and left
Southern Sudanese society devastated by humanitarian crises and
economic deterioration. Peace talks resulted in a US-backed
Comprehensive Peace Agreement, signed in January 2005, which
granted the South a six-year period of autonomy followed by a
referendum on final status. The result of this referendum, held in
January 2011, was a vote of 98% in favor of secession.<br/>
         <br/>
Since independence, South Sudan has struggled to form a viable
governing system and has been plagued by widespread corruption,
political conflict, and communal violence. In December 2013,
conflict erupted between forces loyal to President Salva KIIR, a
Dinka, and forces loyal to Vice President Riek MACHAR, a Nuer. The
conflict quickly spread throughout the country and unfolded along
ethnic lines, killing tens of thousands and creating a dire
humanitarian crisis, with millions of South Sudanese displaced and
food insecure. KIIR and MACHAR signed a peace agreement in August
2015 that created a Transitional Government of National Unity in
April 2016. However, in July 2016, renewed fighting broke out in
Juba between KIIR and MACHAR’s forces, plunging the country back
into conflict and drawing in additional armed opposition groups,
including those in the southern Equatoria region that had largely
stayed out of the first round of civil war. A "revitalized" peace
agreement was signed in September 2018, which mostly ended the
fighting. The government and most armed opposition groups agreed
that they would form a unified national army, create a transitional
government by May 2019, and prepare for elections in December 2022.
Subsequent extensions pushed elections to late 2023, and the
transitional government was formed in February 2020, when MACHAR
returned to Juba as first vice president. Since 2020,
implementation of the peace agreement has been stalled as the
parties wrangle over power-sharing arrangements, contributing to an
uptick in communal violence and the country’s worst food security
crisis since independence, with 7 of 11 million South Sudanese
citizens in need of humanitarian assistance.</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Geography">
      <subsection title="Location">East-Central Africa; south of Sudan, north of Uganda and Kenya,
west of Ethiopia</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geographic coordinates">8 00 N, 30 00 E</subsection>
      <subsection title="Map references">Africa</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area">total: 644,329 sq km<br/>
         <br/>
land: NA<br/>
         <br/>
water: NA<br/>country
comparison to the world: 44</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area - comparative">more than four times the size of Georgia; slightly smaller than
Texas</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land boundaries">total: 6,018 km<br/>
         <br/>
border countries (6): Central African Republic
1,055 km; Democratic Republic of the Congo 714 km; Ethiopia 1,299
km; Kenya 317 km; Sudan 2,158 km; Uganda 475 km<br/>
         <br/>
note: South Sudan-Sudan boundary represents 1
January 1956 alignment; final alignment pending negotiations and
demarcation; final sovereignty status of Abyei Area pending
negotiations between South Sudan and Sudan</subsection>
      <subsection title="Coastline">0 km (landlocked)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maritime claims">none (landlocked)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">hot with seasonal rainfall influenced by the annual shift of the
Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone; rainfall heaviest in upland areas
of the south and diminishes to the north</subsection>
      <subsection title="Terrain">plains in the north and center rise to southern highlands along
the border with Uganda and Kenya; the White Nile, flowing north out
of the uplands of Central Africa, is the major geographic feature
of the country; The Sudd (a name derived from floating vegetation
that hinders navigation) is a large swampy area of more than
100,000 sq km fed by the waters of the White Nile that dominates
the center of the country</subsection>
      <subsection title="Elevation">highest point: Kinyeti 3,187 m<br/>
         <br/>
lowest point: White Nile 381 m</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural resources">hydropower, fertile agricultural land, gold, diamonds,
petroleum, hardwoods, limestone, iron ore, copper, chromium ore,
zinc, tungsten, mica, silver</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">agricultural land: 45% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
arable land: 4.4% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent pasture: 40.7% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
forest: 11.3% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
other: 43.5% (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Irrigated land">1,000 sq km (2012)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major rivers (by length in km)">Nile (shared with Rwanda [s], Tanzania, Uganda, Sudan, and Egypt
[m]) - 6,650 km<br/>
note – [s] after country name indicates river
source; [m] after country name indicates river mouth</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Congo (3,730,881 sq km),
(Mediterranean Sea) Nile (3,254,853 sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">clusters found in urban areas, particularly in the western
interior and around the White Nile as shown in this <br/>population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geography - note">landlocked; The Sudd is a vast swamp in the north central region
of South Sudan, formed by the White Nile, its size is variable but
can reach some 15% of the country's total area during the rainy
season; it is one of the world's largest wetlands</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="People and Society">
      <subsection title="Population">11,544,905 (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 82</subsection>
      <subsection title="Nationality">noun: South Sudanese (singular and
plural)<br/>
         <br/>
adjective: South Sudanese</subsection>
      <subsection title="Ethnic groups">Dinka (Jieng) approximately 35-40%, Nuer (Naath) approximately
15%, Shilluk (Chollo), Azande, Bari, Kakwa, Kuku, Murle, Mandari,
Didinga, Ndogo, Bviri, Lndi, Anuak, Bongo, Lango, Dungotona,
Acholi, Baka, Fertit (2011 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: Figures are estimations due to population
changes during South Sudan's civil war and the lack of updated
demographic studies</subsection>
      <subsection title="Languages">English (official), Arabic (includes Juba and Sudanese
variants), ethnic languages include Dinka, Nuer, Bari, Zande,
Shilluk<br/>
         <br/>
major-language sample(s):<br/>
The World Factbook, the indispensable source for basic information.
(English)<br/>
         <br/>
كتاب حقائق العالم، المصدر الذي لا يمكن الاستغناء عنه للمعلومات
الأساسية (Arabic)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Religions">Christian 60.5%, folk religion 32.9%, Muslim 6.2%, other &lt;1%,
unaffiliated &lt;1% (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Demographic profile">South Sudan, independent from Sudan since July 2011 after
decades of civil war, is one of the world’s poorest countries and
ranks among the lowest in many socioeconomic categories. Problems
are exacerbated by ongoing tensions with Sudan over oil revenues
and land borders, fighting between government forces and rebel
groups, and inter-communal violence. Most of the population lives
off of farming, while smaller numbers rely on animal husbandry;
abput 80% of the populace lives in rural areas. The maternal
mortality rate is among the world’s highest for a variety of
reasons, including a shortage of health care workers, facilities,
and supplies; poor roads and a lack of transport; and cultural
beliefs that prevent women from seeking obstetric care. Most women
marry and start having children early, giving birth at home with
the assistance of traditional birth attendants, who are unable to
handle complications.Educational attainment is extremely poor due to the lack of
schools, qualified teachers, and materials. Only one-third of the
population is literate (the rate is even lower among women), and
half live below the poverty line. Teachers and students are also
struggling with the switch from Arabic to English as the language
of instruction. Many adults missed out on schooling because of
warfare and displacement.More than 2 million South Sudanese have sought refuge in
neighboring countries since the current conflict began in December
2013. Another 2.2 million South Sudanese are internally displaced
as of October 2022. Despite South Sudan’s instability and lack of
infrastructure and social services, more than 275,000 people had
fled to South Sudan to escape fighting in Sudan as of December
2022.</subsection>
      <subsection title="Age structure">0-14 years: 41.58% (male 2,238,534/female
2,152,685)<br/>
         <br/>
15-24 years: 21.28% (male 1,153,108/female
1,094,568)<br/>
         <br/>
25-54 years: 30.67% (male 1,662,409/female
1,577,062)<br/>
         <br/>
55-64 years: 3.93% (male 228,875/female
186,571)<br/>
         <br/>
65 years and over: 2.53% (male 153,502/female
113,930) (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Dependency ratios">total dependency ratio: 80.8<br/>
         <br/>
youth dependency ratio: 74.7<br/>
         <br/>
elderly dependency ratio: 6.1<br/>
         <br/>
potential support ratio: 18.4 (2021 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Median age">total: 18.6 years<br/>
         <br/>
male: 18.9 years<br/>
         <br/>
female: 18.3 years (2020 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 208</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population growth rate">4.91% (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 2</subsection>
      <subsection title="Birth rate">37.69 births/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 9</subsection>
      <subsection title="Death rate">9.52 deaths/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 46</subsection>
      <subsection title="Net migration rate">20.97 migrant(s)/1,000 population (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 2</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">clusters found in urban areas, particularly in the western
interior and around the White Nile as shown in this <br/>population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">urban population: 21.2% of total population
(2023)<br/>
         <br/>
rate of urbanization: 4.12% annual rate of change
(2020-25 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major urban areas - population">459,000 JUBA (capital) (2023)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sex ratio">at birth: 1.05 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
0-14 years: 1.04 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
15-24 years: 1.03 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
25-54 years: 1.04 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
55-64 years: 1.19 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
65 years and over: 1.28 male(s)/female<br/>
         <br/>
total population: 1.05 male(s)/female (2022
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maternal mortality ratio">1,150 deaths/100,000 live births (2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 1</subsection>
      <subsection title="Infant mortality rate">total: 63.18 deaths/1,000 live births<br/>
         <br/>
male: 69.06 deaths/1,000 live births<br/>
         <br/>
female: 57 deaths/1,000 live births (2022
est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 8</subsection>
      <subsection title="Life expectancy at birth">total population: 59.16 years<br/>
         <br/>
male: 57.43 years<br/>
         <br/>
female: 60.97 years (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 221</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total fertility rate">5.32 children born/woman (2022 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 8</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gross reproduction rate">2.54 (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Contraceptive prevalence rate">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Drinking water source">improved: urban: 88.7% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 75.8% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 78.4% of population<br/>
         <br/>
unimproved: urban: 11.3% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 24.2% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 21.6% of population (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Current health expenditure">5.3% of GDP (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sanitation facility access">improved: urban: 60.6% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 15.5% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 24.6% of population<br/>
         <br/>
unimproved: urban: 39.4% of population<br/>
         <br/>
rural: 84.5% of population<br/>
         <br/>
total: 75.4% of population (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="HIV/AIDS - adult prevalence rate">2.1% (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 20</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">degree of risk: very high (2020)<br/>
         <br/>
food or waterborne diseases: bacterial and
protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever<br/>
         <br/>
vectorborne diseases: malaria, dengue fever,
Trypanosomiasis-Gambiense (African sleeping sickness)<br/>
         <br/>
water contact diseases: schistosomiasis<br/>
         <br/>
animal contact diseases: rabies<br/>
         <br/>
respiratory diseases: meningococcal
meningitis<br/>
         <br/>
note: on 21 March 2022, the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a Travel Alert for polio in
Africa; South Sudan is currently considered a high risk to
travelers for circulating vaccine-derived polioviruses (cVDPV);
vaccine-derived poliovirus (VDPV) is a strain of the weakened
poliovirus that was initially included in oral polio vaccine (OPV)
and that has changed over time and behaves more like the wild
or naturally occurring virus; this means it can be spread more
easily to people who are unvaccinated against polio and who come in
contact with the stool or respiratory secretions, such as from a
sneeze, of an “infected” person who received oral polio vaccine;
the CDC recommends that before any international travel, anyone
unvaccinated, incompletely vaccinated, or with an unknown polio
vaccination status should complete the routine polio vaccine
series; before travel to any high-risk destination, the CDC
recommends that adults who previously completed the full, routine
polio vaccine series receive a single, lifetime booster dose of
polio vaccine</subsection>
      <subsection title="Obesity - adult prevalence rate">6.6% (2014)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 165</subsection>
      <subsection title="Children under the age of 5 years underweight">NA</subsection>
      <subsection title="Currently married women (ages 15-49)">72% (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Education expenditures">1.5% of GDP (2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 191</subsection>
      <subsection title="Literacy">definition: age 15 and over can read and
write<br/>
         <br/>
total population: 34.5%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 40.3%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 28.9% (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">total: 21%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 21.8%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 20.2% (2021 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Environment">
      <subsection title="Environment - current issues">water pollution; inadequate supplies of potable water; wildlife
conservation and loss of biodiversity; deforestation; soil erosion;
desertification; periodic drought</subsection>
      <subsection title="Environment - international agreements">party to: Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate
Change-Paris Agreement, Desertification, Ozone Layer Protection,
Wetlands<br/>
         <br/>
signed, but not ratified: none of the selected
agreements</subsection>
      <subsection title="Air pollutants">particulate matter emissions: 41.12 micrograms
per cubic meter (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
carbon dioxide emissions: 1.73 megatons (2016
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
methane emissions: 7.61 megatons (2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">hot with seasonal rainfall influenced by the annual shift of the
Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone; rainfall heaviest in upland areas
of the south and diminishes to the north</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">agricultural land: 45% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
arable land: 4.4% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
permanent pasture: 40.7% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
forest: 11.3% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
other: 43.5% (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">urban population: 21.2% of total population
(2023)<br/>
         <br/>
rate of urbanization: 4.12% annual rate of change
(2020-25 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Revenue from forest resources">forest revenues: 2.65% of GDP (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 25</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">degree of risk: very high (2020)<br/>
         <br/>
food or waterborne diseases: bacterial and
protozoal diarrhea, hepatitis A and E, and typhoid fever<br/>
         <br/>
vectorborne diseases: malaria, dengue fever,
Trypanosomiasis-Gambiense (African sleeping sickness)<br/>
         <br/>
water contact diseases: schistosomiasis<br/>
         <br/>
animal contact diseases: rabies<br/>
         <br/>
respiratory diseases: meningococcal
meningitis<br/>
         <br/>
note: on 21 March 2022, the US Centers for Disease
Control and Prevention (CDC) issued a Travel Alert for polio in
Africa; South Sudan is currently considered a high risk to
travelers for circulating vaccine-derived polioviruses (cVDPV);
vaccine-derived poliovirus (VDPV) is a strain of the weakened
poliovirus that was initially included in oral polio vaccine (OPV)
and that has changed over time and behaves more like the wild
or naturally occurring virus; this means it can be spread more
easily to people who are unvaccinated against polio and who come in
contact with the stool or respiratory secretions, such as from a
sneeze, of an “infected” person who received oral polio vaccine;
the CDC recommends that before any international travel, anyone
unvaccinated, incompletely vaccinated, or with an unknown polio
vaccination status should complete the routine polio vaccine
series; before travel to any high-risk destination, the CDC
recommends that adults who previously completed the full, routine
polio vaccine series receive a single, lifetime booster dose of
polio vaccine</subsection>
      <subsection title="Food insecurity">widespread lack of access: due to economic
downturn, civil insecurity, lingering impact of floods and
prolonged conflict - despite sustained humanitarian
assistance, food insecurity still affects large segments of the
population, driven by macroeconomic challenges that have resulted
in rampant food and non-food inflation, insufficient food supplies
due to a stagnant agricultural production, livelihood losses owing
to consecutive years with widespread floods and the escalation of
organized violence at the sub-national level since 2020; about 7.74
million people, approximately 63% of the total population, were
estimated to be severely food insecure during the lean season
between April and July 2022 (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waste and recycling">municipal solid waste generated annually:
2,680,681 tons (2013 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major rivers (by length in km)">Nile (shared with Rwanda [s], Tanzania, Uganda, Sudan, and Egypt
[m]) - 6,650 km<br/>
note – [s] after country name indicates river
source; [m] after country name indicates river mouth</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Congo (3,730,881 sq km),
(Mediterranean Sea) Nile (3,254,853 sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total water withdrawal">municipal: 193 million cubic meters (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
industrial: 225 million cubic meters (2017
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
agricultural: 240 million cubic meters (2017
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total renewable water resources">49.5 billion cubic meters (2019 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Government">
      <subsection title="Country name">conventional long form: Republic of South
Sudan<br/>
         <br/>
conventional short form: South Sudan<br/>
         <br/>
etymology: self-descriptive name from the
country's former position within Sudan prior to independence; the
name "Sudan" derives from the Arabic "bilad-as-sudan" meaning "Land
of the Black [peoples]"</subsection>
      <subsection title="Government type">presidential republic</subsection>
      <subsection title="Capital">name: Juba<br/>
         <br/>
geographic coordinates: 04 51 N, 31 37 E<br/>
         <br/>
time difference: UTC+2 (8 hours ahead of
Washington, DC, during Standard Time)<br/>
         <br/>
etymology: the name derives from Djouba, another
name for the Bari people of South Sudan</subsection>
      <subsection title="Administrative divisions">10 states; Central Equatoria, Eastern Equatoria, Jonglei, Lakes,
Northern Bahr el Ghazal, Unity, Upper Nile, Warrap, Western Bahr el
Ghazal, Western Equatoria; note - in 2015, the creation of 28 new
states was announced and in 2017 four additional states; following
the February 2020 peace agreement, the country was reportedly again
reorganized into the 10 original states, plus 2 administrative
areas, Pibor and Ruweng, and 1 special administrative status area,
Abyei (which is disputed between South Sudan and Sudan); this
latest administrative revision has not yet been vetted by the US
Board on Geographic Names</subsection>
      <subsection title="Independence">9 July 2011 (from Sudan)</subsection>
      <subsection title="National holiday">Independence Day, 9 July (2011)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Constitution">history: previous 2005 (preindependence);
latest signed 7 July 2011, effective 9 July 2011 (Transitional
Constitution of the Republic of South Sudan, 2011); note - new
constitution pending establishment under the 2018 peace
agreement<br/>
         <br/>
amendments: proposed by the National Legislature
or by the president of the republic; passage requires submission of
the proposal to the Legislature at least one month prior to
consideration, approval by at least two-thirds majority vote in
both houses of the Legislature, and assent of the president;
amended 2013, 2015, 2018</subsection>
      <subsection title="Citizenship">citizenship by birth: no<br/>
         <br/>
citizenship by descent only: at least one parent
must be a citizen of South Sudan<br/>
         <br/>
dual citizenship recognized: yes<br/>
         <br/>
residency requirement for naturalization: 10
years</subsection>
      <subsection title="Suffrage">18 years of age; universal</subsection>
      <subsection title="Executive branch">chief of state: President Salva KIIR Mayardit
(since 9 July 2011); Vice Presidents TABAN Deng Gai, Riek MACHAR
Teny Dhurgon, James Wani IGGA, Rebecca Nyandeng Chol GARANG de
Mabior, Hussein ABDELBAGI Ayii (since 22 February 2020); note - the
president is both chief of state and head of government; TABAN
served as First Vice President from 23 July 2016 to February
2020<br/>
         <br/>
head of government: President Salva KIIR Mayardit
(since 9 July 2011); Vice Presidents TABAN Deng Gai, Riek MACHAR
Teny Dhurgon, James Wani IGGA, Rebecca Nyandeng Chol GARANG de
Mabior, Hussein ABDELBAGI Ayii (since 22 February 2020); note -
TABAN served as First Vice President from 23 July 2016 to February
2020<br/>
         <br/>
cabinet: National Council of Ministers appointed
by the president, approved by the Transitional National Legislative
Assembly<br/>
         <br/>
elections/appointments: president directly elected
by simple majority popular vote for a 4-year term (eligible for a
second term); election last held on 11-15 April 2010 (next election
scheduled for 2015 but postponed to 2018, then 2021, and again to
2023)<br/>
         <br/>
election results: 2010: Salva KIIR
Mayardit elected leader of then-Southern Sudan in 2010; percent of
vote - Salva KIIR Mayardit (SPLM) 93%, Lam AKOL (SPLM-DC) 7%</subsection>
      <subsection title="Legislative branch">description: bicameral National Legislature
consists of:<br/>
Council of States, pending establishment as stipulated by the 2018
peace deal<br/>
Transitional National Legislative Assembly (TNLA), established on 4
August 2016, in accordance with the August 2015 Agreement on the
Resolution of the Conflict in the Republic of South Sudan; note -
originally 400 seats; the TNLA was expanded to 550 members from 400
and reestablished in May 2020 under the 2018 peace agreement<br/>
         <br/>
elections: Council of States - pending
establishment as stipulated by the 2018 peace deal<br/>
Transitional National Legislative Assembly - 550 members; percent
of vote by party - NA; seats by party - 332 SPLM, 128 SPLM-IO, 90
other political parties; composition - NA<br/>
         <br/>
election results: Council of States - percent of
vote by party - NA; seats by party - SPLM 20, unknown 30;
composition - men 44, women 6, percent of women 12%<br/>
National Legislative Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA;
seats by party - SPLM 251, DCP 10, independent 6, unknown 133;
composition - men 291, women 109, percent of women 27.3%; note -
total National Legislature percent of women 25.6%</subsection>
      <subsection title="Judicial branch">highest court(s): Supreme Court of South Sudan
- pending formation (will likely consist of a chief and deputy
chief justices as well as 9 other justices)<br/>
         <br/>
judge selection and term of office: justices will
be appointed by the president upon proposal of the pending Judicial
Service Council, likely consisting of a 9-member judicial and
administrative body; justice tenure to be set by the National
Legislature<br/>
         <br/>
subordinate courts: national level - Courts of
Appeal; High Courts; County Courts; state level - High Courts;
County Courts; customary courts; other specialized courts and
tribunals</subsection>
      <subsection title="Political parties and leaders">Democratic Change or DC<br/>
Democratic Forum or DF<br/>
Labour Party or LPSS [Federico Awi VUNI]<br/>
South Sudan Opposition Alliance or SSOA [Hussein ABDELBAGI
Ayii]<br/>
Sudan African National Union or SANU [Toby MADOUT]<br/>
Sudan People's Liberation Movement or SPLM [Salva KIIR
Mayardit]<br/>
Sudan People’s Liberation Movement-In Opposition or SPLM-IO [Riek
MACHAR Teny Dhurgon]<br/>
United Democratic Salvation Front or
UDSF    <br/>
United South Sudan African Party or USSAP [Louis Pasquale ALEU,
Secretary]<br/>
United South Sudan Party or USSP [Paulino LUKUDU Obede]
   note:</subsection>
      <subsection title="International organization participation">AU, FAO, G-77, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO,
IMF, Interpol, IOM, IPU, ITU, MIGA, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UPU, WCO,
WHO, WMO</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation in the US">chief of mission: Ambassador Philip Jada NATANA
(since 17 September 2018)<br/>
         <br/>
chancery: 1015 31st Street NW, Suite 300,
Washington, DC 20007<br/>
         <br/>
telephone: [1] (202) 600-2238<br/>
         <br/>
FAX: [1] (202) 644-9910<br/>
         <br/>
email address and website:<br/>
info.ssdembassy@gmail.com<br/>
         <br/>
         <br/>https://www.southsudanembassyusa.org/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation from the US">chief of mission: Ambassador (vacant); Charge
d'Affaires William FLENS (since 4 June 2022)<br/>
         <br/>
         <br/>
embassy: Kololo Road adjacent to the EU's
compound, Juba<br/>
         <br/>
mailing address: 4420 Juba Place, Washington
DC  20521-4420<br/>
         <br/>
telephone: [211] 912-105-188<br/>
         <br/>
email address and website:<br/>
ACSJuba@state.gov<br/>
         <br/>
         <br/>https://ss.usembassy.gov/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Flag description">three equal horizontal bands of black (top), red, and green; the
red band is edged in white; a blue isosceles triangle based on the
hoist side contains a gold, five-pointed star; black represents the
people of South Sudan, red the blood shed in the struggle for
freedom, green the verdant land, and blue the waters of the Nile;
the gold star represents the unity of the states making up South
Sudan<br/>
         <br/>
note: resembles the flag of Kenya; one of only two
national flags to display six colors as part of its primary design,
the other is South Africa's</subsection>
      <subsection title="National symbol(s)">African fish eagle; national colors: red, green, blue, yellow,
black, white</subsection>
      <subsection title="National anthem">name: "South Sudan Oyee!" (Hooray!)<br/>
         <br/>
lyrics/music: collective of 49 poets/Juba
University students and teachers<br/>
         <br/>
note: adopted 2011; anthem selected in a national
contest</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Economy">
      <subsection title="Economic overview">low-income, oil-based Sahelian economy; extreme poverty and food
insecurity; COVID-19 and ongoing violence threaten socioeconomic
potential; environmentally fragile; ongoing land and property
rights issues; natural resource rich but lacks infrastructure</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP (purchasing power parity)">$20.01 billion (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$21.1 billion (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$24.52 billion (2015 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: data are in 2017 dollars<br/>country
comparison to the world: 152</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP growth rate">-5.2% (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-13.9% (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-0.2% (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 212</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP per capita">$1,600 (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$1,700 (2016 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$2,100 (2015 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
note: data are in 2017 dollars<br/>country
comparison to the world: 218</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP (official exchange rate)">$3.06 billion (2017 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Inflation rate (consumer prices)">10.52% (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
29.68% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
87.24% (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 205</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by end use">household consumption: 34.9% (2011 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
government consumption: 17.1% (2011 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
investment in fixed capital: 10.4% (2011
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports of goods and services: 64.9% (2011
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports of goods and services: -27.2% (2011
est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Agricultural products">milk, sorghum, vegetables, cassava, goat milk, fruit, beef,
sesame seed, sheep milk, mutton</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force">4.278 million (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 94</subsection>
      <subsection title="Unemployment rate">13.91% (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
14.03% (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
12.23% (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 185</subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">total: 21%<br/>
         <br/>
male: 21.8%<br/>
         <br/>
female: 20.2% (2021 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 77</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population below poverty line">76.4% (2016 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gini Index coefficient - distribution of family income">46 (2010 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 23</subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget">revenues: $259.6 million (FY2017/18 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
expenditures: $298.6 million (FY2017/18 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget surplus (+) or deficit (-)">-1.3% (of GDP) (FY2017/18 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 87</subsection>
      <subsection title="Public debt">62.7% of GDP (2017 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
86.6% of GDP (2016 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 77</subsection>
      <subsection title="Taxes and other revenues">8.5% (of GDP) (FY2017/18 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 206</subsection>
      <subsection title="Current account balance">-$6.55 million (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-$1.718 billion (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
-$193.95 million (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 80</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports">$4.652 billion (2021 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars<br/>
         <br/>
$2.344 billion (2020 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars<br/>
         <br/>
$3.641 billion (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 132</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - partners">China 88%, United Arab Emirates 5% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - commodities">crude petroleum, gold, forage crops, lumber, insect resins
(2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports">$4.037 billion (2021 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars<br/>
         <br/>
$4.245 billion (2020 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars<br/>
         <br/>
$3.893 billion (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 151</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - partners">United Arab Emirates 37%, Kenya 18%, China 18% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - commodities">cars, delivery trucks, packaged medicines, foodstuffs, clothing
and apparel (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Reserves of foreign exchange and gold">$183,614,800 (31 December 2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$378,281,700 (31 December 2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
$36,396,400 (31 December 2018 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 186</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exchange rates">South Sudanese pounds (SSP) per US dollar -<br/>
         <br/>
306.355 (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
165.907 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
157.999 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
141.386 (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
113.648 (2017 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Energy">
      <subsection title="Electricity access">electrification - total population: 28.2%
(2018)<br/>
         <br/>
electrification - urban areas: 46.8% (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
electrification - rural areas: 23.6% (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity">installed generating capacity: 121,000 kW (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 531.66 million kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 kWh (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
transmission/distribution losses: 26 million kWh
(2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity generation sources">fossil fuels: 99.2% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
nuclear: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
solar: 0.8% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
wind: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
hydroelectricity: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
tide and wave: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
geothermal: 0% of total installed capacity (2020
est.)<br/>
         <br/>
biomass and waste: 0% of total installed capacity
(2020 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Coal">production: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 metric tons (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
proven reserves: 0 metric tons (2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Petroleum">total petroleum production: 157,100 bbl/day
(2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
refined petroleum consumption: 12,900 bbl/day
(2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
crude oil and lease condensate exports: 126,500
bbl/day (2018 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
crude oil and lease condensate imports: 0 bbl/day
(2018 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - production">0 bbl/day (2017 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 205</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - exports">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 205</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - imports">7,160 bbl/day (2015 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 157</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural gas">production: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
consumption: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
exports: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
imports: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
proven reserves: 0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Carbon dioxide emissions">1.778 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from coal and metallurgical coke: 0 metric tonnes
of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from petroleum and other liquids: 1.778 million
metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
from consumed natural gas: 0 metric tonnes of CO2
(2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 161</subsection>
      <subsection title="Energy consumption per capita">2.404 million Btu/person (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 185</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Communications">
      <subsection title="Telephones - mobile cellular">total subscriptions: 2,221,970 (2019)<br/>
         <br/>
subscriptions per 100 inhabitants: 20.09
(2019)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 146</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telecommunication systems">general assessment: following a referendum,
oil-rich South Sudan seceded from Sudan in 2011 and became an
independent nation; having been deprived of investment for decades,
it inherited one of the least developed telecom markets in the
world; there was once investment activity among mobile network
operators who sought to expand their networks in some areas of the
country; operators in the telecom sector placed themselves in
survival mode and are hoping for a political settlement and a
return to some degree of social stability; South Sudan has one of
the lowest mobile penetration rates in Africa; growth in the sector
in coming years is premised on a resolution to the political crisis
and a recovery of the country’s economy; the virtually untapped
internet and broadband market also depends to a large extent on the
country gaining access to international fiber cables and on a
national backbone network being in place; sophisticated
infrastructure solutions are needed to reach the 80% of the
population that live outside of the main urban centers; some
improvement has followed from the cable link in February 2020 which
connects Juba directly to the company’s submarine landing station
at Mombasa; the cable was South Sudan’s first direct international
fiber link, and has helped drive down the price of retail internet
services for residential and business customers; a second cable
linking to the border with Kenya was completed in December 2021
(2022)<br/>
         <br/>
domestic: fixed-line less than 1 per 100
subscriptions, mobile-cellular roughly 12 per 100 persons
(2020)<br/>
         <br/>
international: country code - 211 (2017)<br/>
         <br/>
note: the COVID-19 pandemic continues to have a
significant impact on production and supply chains globally; since
2020, some aspects of the telecom sector have experienced a
downturn, particularly in mobile device production; progress toward
5G implementation has resumed, as well as upgrades to
infrastructure; consumer spending on telecom services has increased
due to the surge in demand for capacity and bandwidth; the crucial
nature of telecom services as a tool for work and school from home
is still evident, and the spike in this area has seen growth
opportunities for development of new tools and increased
services</subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadcast media">a single TV channel and a radio station are controlled by the
government; several community and commercial FM stations are
operational, mostly sponsored by outside aid donors; some foreign
radio broadcasts are available</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet country code">.ss</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet users">total: 783,561 (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
percent of population: 7% (2020 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 151</subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadband - fixed subscriptions">total: 200 (2019 est.)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 212</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transportation">
      <subsection title="National air transport system">number of registered air carriers: 2
(2020)<br/>
         <br/>
inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
carriers: 2<br/>
         <br/>
annual freight traffic on registered air carriers:
0 mt-km</subsection>
      <subsection title="Civil aircraft registration country code prefix">Z8</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports">total: 89 (2021)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 63</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with paved runways">total: 4<br/>
         <br/>
over 3,047 m: 1<br/>
         <br/>
2,438 to 3,047 m: 2<br/>
         <br/>
1,524 to 2,437 m: 1 (2021)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with unpaved runways">total: 84<br/>
         <br/>
2,438 to 3,047 m: 1<br/>
         <br/>
1,524 to 2,437 m: 12<br/>
         <br/>
914 to 1,523 m: 38<br/>
         <br/>
under 914 m: 33 (2021)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Heliports">3 (2021)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Railways">total: 248 km (2018)<br/>
         <br/>
note: a narrow gauge, single-track railroad
between Babonosa (Sudan) and Wau, the only existing rail system,
was repaired in 2010 with $250 million in UN funds, but is not
currently operational<br/>country
comparison to the world: 126</subsection>
      <subsection title="Roadways">total: 90,200 km (2019)<br/>
         <br/>
paved: 300 km (2019)<br/>
         <br/>
unpaved: 89,900 km (2019)<br/>
         <br/>
note: most of the road network is unpaved and much
of it is in disrepair; the Juba-Nimule highway connecting Juba to
the border with Uganda is the main paved road in South
Sudan <br/>country
comparison to the world: 54</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waterways">see entry for Sudan</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Military and Security">
      <subsection title="Military and security forces">South Sudan People’s Defense Force (SSPDF): Ground Force
(includes Presidential Guard, aka Tiger Division), Air Force, Air
Defense Forces; National (or Necessary) Unified Forces (NUF)
(2022)<br/>
         <br/>
note 1: the NUF are being formed by retraining
rebel and pro-government militia fighters into military, police,
and other government security forces; in August 2022, South Sudan
held the first graduation ceremony for retrained
personnel<br/>
         <br/>
note 2: numerous irregular forces operate in the
country with official knowledge, including militias operated by the
National Security Service (an internal security force under the
Ministry of National Security) and proxy forces</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military expenditures">2% of GDP (2021 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
2% of GDP (2020 est.)<br/>
         <br/>
3.1% of GDP (2019 est.) (approximately $1.62 billion)<br/>
         <br/>
3.2% of GDP (2018 est.) (approximately $1.54 billion)<br/>
         <br/>
2.1% of GDP (2017 est.) (approximately $660 million)<br/>country
comparison to the world: 66</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military and security service personnel strengths">estimated 150-200,000 active personnel, mostly ground forces
with small contingents of air and riverine forces (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
note: some active SSPDF personnel may be militia;
the National/Necessary Unified Forces (NUF) will have some
50-80,000 personnel; the initial batch of 22,000 NUF personnel
completed training in August 2022</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military equipment inventories and acquisitions">the SSPDF inventory is primarily of Soviet origin; South Sudan
has been under a UN arms embargo since 2018 (2023)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military service age and obligation">18 is the legal minimum age for compulsory and voluntary
military service; conscription only for men; women may volunteer;
12-24 months service (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
note: in 2019, women made up less than 10% of the
active military</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military - note">the South Sudan People’s Defense Force (SSPDF), formerly the
Sudan People’s Liberation Army (SPLA), was founded as a guerrilla
movement against the Sudanese Government in 1983 and participated
in the Second Sudanese Civil War (1983-2005); the Juba Declaration
that followed the Comprehensive Peace Agreement of 2005 unified the
SPLA and the South Sudan Defense Forces (SSDF), the second-largest
rebel militia remaining from the civil war, under the SPLA name; in
2017, the SPLA was renamed the South Sudan Defense Forces (SSDF)
and in September 2018 was renamed again as the SSPDF<br/>
         <br/>
the United Nations Mission in South Sudan (UNMISS) has operated in
the country since 2011 with the objectives of consolidating peace
and security and helping establish conditions for the successful
economic and political development of South Sudan; UNMISS had about
15,000 personnel deployed in the country as of 2022<br/>
         <br/>
United Nations Interim Security Force for Abyei (UNISFA) has
operated in the disputed Abyei region along the border between
Sudan and South Sudan since 2011; UNISFA's mission includes
ensuring security, protecting civilians, strengthening the capacity
of the Abyei Police Service, de-mining, monitoring/verifying the
redeployment of armed forces from the area, and facilitating the
flow of humanitarian aid; as of 2022, UNISFA had approximately
2,500 military and police personnel</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transnational Issues">
      <subsection title="Disputes - international">South Sudan- Central African Republic: periodic violent
skirmishes persist among related pastoral populations along the
border with the Central African Republic over water and grazing
rights<br/>
         <br/>
South Sudan-Democratic Republic of the Congo: none
identified<br/>
         <br/>
South Sudan-Ethiopia: the unresolved demarcation of the
boundary and lack of clear limitation create substantial room for
territorial conflict both locally among the border populations and
between the two capitals; besides a large number of indigenous
farmers, the border region supports refugees and various rebel
groups opposed to the governments in Khartoum and Addis Ababa<br/>
South Sudan-Kenya: the boundary that separates Kenya and
South Sudan's sovereignty is unclear in the Ilemi Triangle and has
been unclear since British colonial times; Kenya has administered
the area since colonial timesSouth Sudan-Sudan: present boundary represents 1
January 1956 alignment, which clearly placed the Kafia Kingi area
(adjacent to Central African Republic) within South Sudan as shown
on US maps although it is mostly occupied by Sudan; final alignment
pending negotiations and demarcation; the final sovereignty status
of Abyei Area pending negotiations between South Sudan and Sudan;
clashes continue in the oil-rich Abyei region; the United Nations
interim security Force for Abyei (UNISFA) has been deployed since
2011, when South Sudan became independent, Sudan accuses South
Sudan of supporting Sudanese rebel groupsSouth Sudan-Uganda: Lord’s Resistance Army operations
in western Equatorial State displace and drive out local
populations and steal grain stores</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refugees and internally displaced persons">refugees (country of origin): 289,840 (Sudan),
15,105 (Democratic Republic of the Congo) (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
IDPs: 2.23 million (alleged coup attempt and
ethnic conflict beginning in December 2013; information is lacking
on those displaced in earlier years by: fighting in Abyei between
the Sudanese Armed Forces and the Sudan People's Liberation Army
(SPLA) in May 2011; clashes between the SPLA and dissident militia
groups in South Sudan; inter-ethnic conflicts over resources and
cattle; attacks from the Lord's Resistance Army; floods and
drought) (2022)<br/>
         <br/>
stateless persons: 10,000 (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Trafficking in persons">tier rating:Tier 3 — South Sudan does not fully meet the minimum standards
for the elimination of trafficking and is not making significant
efforts to do so: the government’s efforts include forming and
staffing an anti-trafficking inter-ministerial task force,
releasing 286 child soldiers, and identifying 19 potential
trafficking victims; however, the recruitment of child soldiers by
security and law enforcement continues and neither was held
criminally responsible; authorities did not investigate or
prosecute forced labor or sex trafficking crimes and made no effort
to identify and protect trafficking victims; authorities continued
to arrest and imprison child sex trafficking victims without
screening for indicators of trafficking (2020)<br/>
         <br/>trafficking profile:</subsection>
   </section>
</country>
