<country>
   <name>Tanzania</name>
   <section title="Photos of Tanzania"/>
   <section title="Introduction">
      <subsection title="Background">Tanzania contains some of Africa’s most iconic national parks
and famous paleoanthropological sites, and its diverse cultural
heritage reflects the multiple ethnolinguistic groups that live in
the country. Its long history of integration into trade networks
spanning the Indian Ocean and the African interior led to the
development of Swahili as a common language in much of east Africa
and the introduction of Islam into the region. A number of
independent coastal and island trading posts in what is now
Tanzania came under Portuguese control after 1498 when they began
to take control of much of the coast and Indian Ocean trade. By
1700, the Sultanate of Oman had become the dominant power in the
region after ousting the Portuguese who were also facing a series
of local uprisings. During the following hundred years, Zanzibar -
an archipelago off the coast of Tanzania - became a hub of Indian
Ocean trade, with Arab and Indian traders establishing and
consolidating trade routes with communities in mainland Tanzania
that contributed to the expansion of the slave trade. Zanzibar
briefly become the capital of the Sultanate of Oman before it split
into separate Omani and Zanzibar Sultanates in 1856. Beginning in
the mid-1800s, European explorers, traders, and Christian
missionaries became more active in the region. The Germans
eventually established control over mainland Tanzania - which they
called Tanganyika - and the British established control over
Zanzibar. Tanganyika later came under British administration after
the German defeat in World War I.Tanganyika gained independence from Great Britain in 1961, and
Zanzibar followed in 1963 as a constitutional monarchy. In
Tanganyika, Julius NYERERE, a charismatic and idealistic socialist,
established a one-party political system that centralized power and
encouraged national self-reliance and rural development. In 1964, a
popular uprising overthrew the Sultan in Zanzibar and either killed
or expelled many of the Arabs and Indians who had dominated the
isles for more than 200 years. Later that year, Tanganyika and
Zanzibar combined to form the United Republic of Tanzania, but
Zanzibar retained considerable autonomy. Their two ruling parties
combined to form the Chama Cha Mapinduzi (CCM) party in 1977.
NYERERE handed over power to Ali Hassan MWINYI in 1985 and remained
CCM chair until 1990. Tanzania held its first multi-party elections
in 1995, but CCM candidates have continued to dominate politics.
Political opposition in Zanzibar has led to four contentious
elections since 1995, in which the ruling party claimed victory
despite international observers' claims of voting irregularities.
In 2001, 35 people in Zanzibar died when soldiers fired on
protestors following the 2000 election. John MAGUFULI won the 2015
presidential election, and the CCM won a two-thirds majority in
Parliament. He was reelected in 2020 and the CCM increased its
majority in an election that was also critiqued by observers.
MAGUFULI died in March 2021 while in office and was
constitutionally succeeded by his vice president, Samia Suluhu
HASSAN.</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Geography">
      <subsection title="Location">Eastern Africa, bordering the Indian Ocean, between Kenya and
Mozambique</subsection>
      <subsection title="Geographic coordinates">6 00 S, 35 00 E</subsection>
      <subsection title="Map references">Africa</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area">
         <note title="total">947,300 sq km</note>
         <note title="land">885,800 sq km</note>
         <note title="water">61,500 sq km</note>
         <note title="note">includes the islands of Mafia, Pemba, and Zanzibar</note>country
comparison to the world: 32</subsection>
      <subsection title="Area - comparative">more than six times the size of Georgia; slightly larger than
twice the size of California</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land boundaries">
         <note title="total">4,161 km</note>
         <note title="border countries (8)">Burundi 589 km; Democratic Republic of the Congo 479 km; Kenya 775 km; Malawi 512 km; Mozambique 840 km; Rwanda 222 km; Uganda 391 km; Zambia 353 km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Coastline">1,424 km</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maritime claims">
         <note title="territorial sea">12 nm</note>
         <note title="exclusive economic zone">200 nm</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">varies from tropical along coast to temperate in highlands</subsection>
      <subsection title="Terrain">plains along coast; central plateau; highlands in north,
south</subsection>
      <subsection title="Elevation">
         <note title="highest point">Kilimanjaro (highest point in Africa) 5,895 m</note>
         <note title="lowest point">Indian Ocean 0 m</note>
         <note title="mean elevation">1,018 m</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural resources">hydropower, tin, phosphates, iron ore, coal, diamonds, gemstones
(including tanzanite, found only in Tanzania), gold, natural gas,
nickel</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">
         <note title="agricultural land">43.7% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="forest">37.3% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="other">19% (2018 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Irrigated land">1,840 sq km (2012)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major lakes (area sq km)">
         <note title="fresh water lake(s)">Lake Victoria (shared with Uganda and Kenya) - 62,940 sq km; Lake Tanganyika (shared with Democratic Republic of Congo, Burundi, and Zambia) - 32,000 sq km; Lake Malawi (shared with Mozambique and Malawi) - 22,490</note>
         <note title="salt water lake(s)">Lake Rukwa - 5,760 sq km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major rivers (by length in km)">Nile (shared with Rwanda [s], Uganda, South Sudan, Sudan, and
Egypt [m]) - 6,650 km
<note title="note">– [s] after country name indicates river source; [m] after country name indicates river mouth</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Congo (3,730,881 sq km),
(Mediterranean Sea) Nile (3,254,853 sq km)
Indian Ocean drainage: Zambezi (1,332,412 sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">the largest and most populous East African country; population
distribution is extremely uneven, but greater population clusters
occur in the northern half of country and along the east coast as
shown in this population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural hazards">flooding on the central plateau during the rainy season;
drought<note title="volcanism">limited volcanic activity; Ol Doinyo Lengai (2,962 m) has emitted lava in recent years; other historically active volcanoes include Kieyo and Meru</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Geography - note">Kilimanjaro is the highest point in Africa and one of only three
mountain ranges on the continent that has glaciers (the others are
Mount Kenya [in Kenya] and the Ruwenzori Mountains [on the
Uganda-Democratic Republic of the Congo border]); Tanzania is
bordered by three of the largest lakes on the continent: Lake
Victoria (the world's second-largest freshwater lake) in the north,
Lake Tanganyika (the world's second deepest) in the west, and Lake
Nyasa (Lake Malawi) in the southwest</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="People and Society">
      <subsection title="Population">63,852,892 (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 23</subsection>
      <subsection title="Nationality">
         <note title="noun">Tanzanian(s)</note>
         <note title="adjective">Tanzanian</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Ethnic groups">mainland - African 99% (of which 95% are Bantu consisting of
more than 130 tribes), other 1% (consisting of Asian, European, and
Arab); Zanzibar - Arab, African, mixed Arab and African</subsection>
      <subsection title="Languages">Kiswahili or Swahili (official), Kiunguja (name for Swahili in
Zanzibar), English (official, primary language of commerce,
administration, and higher education), Arabic (widely spoken in
Zanzibar), many local languages; note - Kiswahili (Swahili) is the
mother tongue of the Bantu people living in Zanzibar and nearby
coastal Tanzania; although Kiswahili is Bantu in structure and
origin, its vocabulary draws on a variety of sources including
Arabic and English; it has become the lingua franca of central and
eastern Africa; the first language of most people is one of the
local languages
<note title="major-language sample(s)">The World Factbook, Chanzo cha Lazima Kuhusu Habari ya Msingi. (Kiswahili)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Religions">Christian 63.1%, Muslim 34.1%, folk religion 1.1%, Buddhist
&lt;1%, Hindu &lt;1%, Jewish &lt;1%, other &lt;1%, unspecified 1.6%
(2020 est.)
<note title="note">Zanzibar is almost entirely Muslim</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Demographic profile">Tanzania has the largest population in East Africa and the
lowest population density; more than a third of the population is
urban. Tanzania’s youthful population – over 60% of the population
is under 25 as of 2020 – is growing rapidly because of the high
total fertility rate of 4.4 children per woman, as of 2022.
Progress in reducing the birth rate has stalled, sustaining the
country’s nearly 3% annual growth rate. The maternal mortality rate
has improved since 2000, yet it remains very high because of early
and frequent pregnancies, inadequate maternal health services, and
a lack of skilled birth attendants – problems that are worse among
poor and rural women. Tanzania has made strides in reducing under-5
and infant mortality rates, but a recent drop in immunization
threatens to undermine gains in child health. Malaria is a leading
killer of children under 5, while HIV is the main source of adult
mortality.For Tanzania, most migration is internal, rural to urban
movement, while some temporary labor migration from towns to
plantations takes place seasonally for harvests. Tanzania was
Africa’s largest refugee-hosting country for decades, hosting
hundreds of thousands of refugees from the Great Lakes region,
primarily Burundi, over the last fifty years. However, the assisted
repatriation and naturalization of tens of thousands of Burundian
refugees between 2002 and 2014 dramatically reduced the refugee
population. Tanzania is increasingly a transit country for illegal
migrants from the Horn of Africa and the Great Lakes region who are
heading to southern Africa for security reasons and/or economic
opportunities. Some of these migrants choose to settle in
Tanzania.</subsection>
      <subsection title="Age structure">
         <note title="0-14 years">42.7% (male 12,632,772/female 12,369,115)</note>
         <note title="15-24 years">20.39% (male 5,988,208/female 5,948,134)</note>
         <note title="25-54 years">30.31% (male 8,903,629/female 8,844,180)</note>
         <note title="55-64 years">3.52% (male 954,251/female 1,107,717)</note>
         <note title="65 years and over">3.08% (male 747,934/female 1,056,905) (2020 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Dependency ratios">
         <note title="total dependency ratio">87.7</note>
         <note title="youth dependency ratio">81.9</note>
         <note title="elderly dependency ratio">5.9</note>
         <note title="potential support ratio">20.4 (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Median age">
         <note title="total">18.2 years</note>
         <note title="male">17.9 years</note>
         <note title="female">18.4 years (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 212</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population growth rate">2.78% (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 13</subsection>
      <subsection title="Birth rate">33.3 births/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 21</subsection>
      <subsection title="Death rate">5.09 deaths/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 192</subsection>
      <subsection title="Net migration rate">-0.41 migrant(s)/1,000 population (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 123</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population distribution">the largest and most populous East African country; population
distribution is extremely uneven, but greater population clusters
occur in the northern half of country and along the east coast as
shown in this population distribution map</subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">
         <note title="urban population">37.4% of total population (2023)</note>
         <note title="rate of urbanization">4.89% annual rate of change (2020-25 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major urban areas - population">262,000 Dodoma (legislative capital) (2018), 7.776 million DAR
ES SALAAM (administrative capital), 1.311 million Mwanza, 800,000
Zanzibar (2023)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sex ratio">
         <note title="at birth">1.03 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="0-14 years">1.02 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="15-24 years">1.01 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="25-54 years">0.99 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="55-64 years">0.92 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="65 years and over">0.7 male(s)/female</note>
         <note title="total population">1 male(s)/female (2022 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Mother's mean age at first birth">19.8 years (2015/16 est.)
<note title="note">data represents median age at first birth among women 20-49</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Maternal mortality ratio">524 deaths/100,000 live births (2017 est.)country
comparison to the world: 19</subsection>
      <subsection title="Infant mortality rate">
         <note title="total">30.87 deaths/1,000 live births</note>
         <note title="male">33.66 deaths/1,000 live births</note>
         <note title="female">28 deaths/1,000 live births (2022 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 49</subsection>
      <subsection title="Life expectancy at birth">
         <note title="total population">70.19 years</note>
         <note title="male">68.42 years</note>
         <note title="female">72.02 years (2022 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 169</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total fertility rate">4.39 children born/woman (2022 est.)country
comparison to the world: 20</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gross reproduction rate">2.13 (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Contraceptive prevalence rate">38.4% (2015/16)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Drinking water source">
         <note title="improved">urban: 95.1% of population</note>
         <note title="unimproved">urban: 4.9% of population</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Current health expenditure">3.8% of GDP (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Physicians density">0.05 physicians/1,000 population (2018)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Hospital bed density">0.7 beds/1,000 population</subsection>
      <subsection title="Sanitation facility access">
         <note title="improved">urban: 89.4% of population</note>
         <note title="unimproved">urban: 10.6% of population</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="HIV/AIDS - adult prevalence rate">4.5% (2021 est.)country
comparison to the world: 12</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">
         <note title="degree of risk">very high (2020)</note>
         <note title="food or waterborne diseases">bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</note>
         <note title="vectorborne diseases">malaria, dengue fever, and Rift Valley fever</note>
         <note title="water contact diseases">schistosomiasis</note>
         <note title="animal contact diseases">rabies</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Obesity - adult prevalence rate">8.4% (2016)country
comparison to the world: 151</subsection>
      <subsection title="Alcohol consumption per capita">
         <note title="total">7.81 liters of pure alcohol (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="beer">0.74 liters of pure alcohol (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="wine">0.09 liters of pure alcohol (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="spirits">0.38 liters of pure alcohol (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="other alcohols">6.6 liters of pure alcohol (2019 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 46</subsection>
      <subsection title="Tobacco use">
         <note title="total">8.7% (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="male">14% (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="female">3.4% (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 141</subsection>
      <subsection title="Children under the age of 5 years underweight">14.6% (2018)country
comparison to the world: 38</subsection>
      <subsection title="Currently married women (ages 15-49)">59.5% (2023 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Child marriage">
         <note title="women married by age 15">5.2%</note>
         <note title="women married by age 18">30.5%</note>
         <note title="men married by age 18">3.9% (2016 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Education expenditures">3.3% of GDP (2021 est.)country
comparison to the world: 147</subsection>
      <subsection title="Literacy">
         <note title="definition">age 15 and over can read and write Kiswahili (Swahili), English, or Arabic</note>
         <note title="total population">77.9%</note>
         <note title="male">83.2%</note>
         <note title="female">73.1% (2015)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="School life expectancy (primary to tertiary education)">
         <note title="total">9 years</note>
         <note title="male">9 years</note>
         <note title="female">9 years (2021)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">
         <note title="total">4.6%</note>
         <note title="male">3.7%</note>
         <note title="female">5.5% (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Environment">
      <subsection title="Environment - current issues">water pollution; improper management of liquid waste; indoor air
pollution caused by the burning of fuel wood or charcoal for
cooking and heating is a large environmental health issue; soil
degradation; deforestation; desertification; destruction of coral
reefs threatens marine habitats; wildlife threatened by illegal
hunting and trade, especially for ivory; loss of biodiversity;
solid waste disposal</subsection>
      <subsection title="Environment - international agreements">
         <note title="party to">Biodiversity, Climate Change, Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol, Climate Change-Paris Agreement, Comprehensive Nuclear Test Ban, Desertification, Endangered Species, Hazardous Wastes, Law of the Sea, Marine Dumping-London Convention, Nuclear Test Ban, Ozone Layer Protection, Ship Pollution, Wetlands, Whaling</note>
         <note title="signed, but not ratified">none of the selected agreements</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Air pollutants">
         <note title="particulate matter emissions">25.59 micrograms per cubic meter (2016 est.)</note>
         <note title="carbon dioxide emissions">11.97 megatons (2016 est.)</note>
         <note title="methane emissions">59.08 megatons (2020 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Climate">varies from tropical along coast to temperate in highlands</subsection>
      <subsection title="Land use">
         <note title="agricultural land">43.7% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="forest">37.3% (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="other">19% (2018 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Urbanization">
         <note title="urban population">37.4% of total population (2023)</note>
         <note title="rate of urbanization">4.89% annual rate of change (2020-25 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Revenue from forest resources">
         <note title="forest revenues">2.19% of GDP (2018 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 32</subsection>
      <subsection title="Revenue from coal">
         <note title="coal revenues">0.02% of GDP (2018 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 45</subsection>
      <subsection title="Major infectious diseases">
         <note title="degree of risk">very high (2020)</note>
         <note title="food or waterborne diseases">bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</note>
         <note title="vectorborne diseases">malaria, dengue fever, and Rift Valley fever</note>
         <note title="water contact diseases">schistosomiasis</note>
         <note title="animal contact diseases">rabies</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Food insecurity">
         <note title="severe localized food insecurity"/>due to
localized shortfalls in staple food production -</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waste and recycling">
         <note title="municipal solid waste generated annually">9,276,995 tons (2012 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major lakes (area sq km)">
         <note title="fresh water lake(s)">Lake Victoria (shared with Uganda and Kenya) - 62,940 sq km; Lake Tanganyika (shared with Democratic Republic of Congo, Burundi, and Zambia) - 32,000 sq km; Lake Malawi (shared with Mozambique and Malawi) - 22,490</note>
         <note title="salt water lake(s)">Lake Rukwa - 5,760 sq km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major rivers (by length in km)">Nile (shared with Rwanda [s], Uganda, South Sudan, Sudan, and
Egypt [m]) - 6,650 km
<note title="note">– [s] after country name indicates river source; [m] after country name indicates river mouth</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Major watersheds (area sq km)">Atlantic Ocean drainage: Congo (3,730,881 sq km),
(Mediterranean Sea) Nile (3,254,853 sq km)
Indian Ocean drainage: Zambezi (1,332,412 sq km)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Total water withdrawal">
         <note title="municipal">527 million cubic meters (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="industrial">25 million cubic meters (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="agricultural">4.632 billion cubic meters (2017 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Total renewable water resources">96.3 billion cubic meters (2019 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Government">
      <subsection title="Country name">
         <note title="conventional long form">United Republic of Tanzania</note>
         <note title="conventional short form">Tanzania</note>
         <note title="local long form">Jamhuri ya Muungano wa Tanzania</note>
         <note title="local short form">Tanzania</note>
         <note title="former">German East Africa, Trust Territory of Tanganyika, Republic of Tanganyika, People's Republic of Zanzibar, United Republic of Tanganyika and Zanzibar</note>
         <note title="etymology">the country's name is a combination of the first letters of Tanganyika and Zanzibar, the two states that merged to form Tanzania in 1964</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Government type">presidential republic</subsection>
      <subsection title="Capital">
         <note title="name">Dar es Salaam (de facto administrative capital), Dodoma (national capital); note - Dodoma, designated the national capital in 1996, serves as the meeting place for the National Assembly and is thus the legislative capital; Dar es Salaam (the original national capital) remains the de facto capital, the country's largest city and commercial center, and the site of the executive branch offices and diplomatic representation</note>
         <note title="geographic coordinates">6 48 S, 39 17 E</note>
         <note title="time difference">UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of Washington, DC, during Standard Time)</note>
         <note title="etymology">Dar es Salaam was the name given by Majid BIN SAID, the first sultan of Zanzibar, to the new city he founded on the Indian Ocean coast; the Arabic name is commonly translated as "abode/home of peace"; Dodoma, in the native Gogo language, means "it has sunk"; supposedly, one day during the rainy season, an elephant drowned in the area; the villagers in that place were so struck by what had occurred, that ever since the locale has been referred to as the place where "it (the elephant) sunk"</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Administrative divisions">31 regions; Arusha, Dar es Salaam, Dodoma, Geita, Iringa,
Kagera, Kaskazini Pemba (Pemba North), Kaskazini Unguja (Zanzibar
North), Katavi, Kigoma, Kilimanjaro, Kusini Pemba (Pemba South),
Kusini Unguja (Zanzibar Central/South), Lindi, Manyara, Mara,
Mbeya, Mjini Magharibi (Zanzibar Urban/West), Morogoro, Mtwara,
Mwanza, Njombe, Pwani (Coast), Rukwa, Ruvuma, Shinyanga, Simiyu,
Singida, Songwe, Tabora, Tanga</subsection>
      <subsection title="Independence">26 April 1964 (Tanganyika united with Zanzibar to form the
United Republic of Tanganyika and Zanzibar); 29 October 1964
(renamed United Republic of Tanzania); notable earlier dates: 9
December 1961 (Tanganyika became independent from UK-administered
UN trusteeship); 10 December 1963 (Zanzibar became independent from
UK)</subsection>
      <subsection title="National holiday">Union Day (Tanganyika and Zanzibar), 26 April (1964)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Constitution">
         <note title="history">several previous; latest adopted 25 April 1977; note - progress enacting a new constitution drafted in 2014 by the Constituent Assembly has stalled</note>
         <note title="amendments">proposed by the National Assembly; passage of amendments to constitutional articles including those on sovereignty of the United Republic, the authorities and powers of the government, the president, the Assembly, and the High Court requires two-thirds majority vote of the mainland Assembly membership and of the Zanzibar House of Representatives membership; House of Representatives approval of other amendments is not required; amended several times, last in 2017</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Legal system">English common law; judicial review of legislative acts limited
to matters of interpretation</subsection>
      <subsection title="International law organization participation">has not submitted an ICJ jurisdiction declaration; accepts ICCt
jurisdiction</subsection>
      <subsection title="Citizenship">
         <note title="citizenship by birth">no</note>
         <note title="citizenship by descent only">at least one parent must be a citizen of Tanzania; if a child is born abroad, the father must be a citizen of Tanzania</note>
         <note title="dual citizenship recognized">no</note>
         <note title="residency requirement for naturalization">5 years</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Suffrage">18 years of age; universal</subsection>
      <subsection title="Executive branch">
         <note title="chief of state">President Samia Suluhu HASSAN (since 19 March 2021); note - the president is both chief of state and head of government; note - President John MAGUFULI died on 17 March 2021; Vice President Philip MPANGO</note>
         <note title="head of government">President Samia Suluhu HASSAN (since 19 March 2021); Vice President Philip MPANGO; Prime Minister Kassim Majaliwa MAJALIWA (since 20 November 2015) has authority over the day-to-day functions of the government, is the leader of government business in the National Assembly, and head of the Cabinet</note>
         <note title="cabinet">Cabinet appointed by the president from among members of the National Assembly</note>
         <note title="elections/appointments">president and vice president directly elected on the same ballot by simple majority popular vote for a 5-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 28 October 2020 (next to be held in October 2025); prime minister appointed by the president</note>
         <note title="election results"/>20202015<note title="note">Zanzibar elects a president as head of government for internal matters; elections were held on 28 October 2020; Hussein MWINYI (CCM) 76.3%, Maalim Seif SHARIF (ACT-Wazalendo) 19.9%, other 3.8%</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Legislative branch">
         <note title="description">unicameral National Assembly or Parliament (Bunge) (393 seats; 264 members directly elected in single-seat constituencies by simple majority vote, 113 women indirectly elected by proportional representation vote, 5 indirectly elected by simple majority vote by the Zanzibar House of Representatives, 10 appointed by the president, and 1 seat reserved for the attorney general; members serve 5-year terms); note - in addition to enacting laws that apply to the entire United Republic of Tanzania, the National Assembly enacts laws that apply only to the mainland; Zanzibar has its own House of Representatives or Baraza La Wawakilishi (82 seats; 50 members directly elected in single-seat constituencies by simple majority vote, 20 women directly elected by proportional representation vote, 10 appointed by the Zanzibar president, 1 seat for the House speaker, and 1 ex-officio seat for the attorney general; elected members serve a 5-year term)</note>
         <note title="elections">Tanzania National Assembly and Zanzibar House of Representatives - elections last held on 28 October 2020 (next National Assembly election to be held in October 2025; next Zanzibar election NA)</note>
         <note title="election results">National Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - CCM 350, Chadema 20, ACT-Wazalendo 4, CUF 3; composition as of early 2021 (388 members) - men 245, women 143, percent of women 36.9%</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Judicial branch">
         <note title="highest court(s)">Court of Appeal of the United Republic of Tanzania (consists of the chief justice and 14 justices); High Court of the United Republic for Mainland Tanzania (consists of the principal judge and 30 judges organized into commercial, land, and labor courts); High Court of Zanzibar (consists of the chief justice and 10 justices)</note>
         <note title="judge selection and term of office">Court of Appeal and High Court justices appointed by the national president after consultation with the Judicial Service Commission for Tanzania, a judicial body of high level judges and 2 members appointed by the national president; Court of Appeal and High Court judges serve until mandatory retirement at age 60, but terms can be extended; High Court of Zanzibar judges appointed by the national president after consultation with the Judicial Commission of Zanzibar; judges can serve until mandatory retirement at age 65</note>
         <note title="subordinate courts">Resident Magistrates Courts; Kadhi courts (for Islamic family matters); district and primary courts</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Political parties and leaders">Alliance for Change and Transparency (Wazalendo) or
ACT-Wazalendo [Zitto KABWE]
Civic United Front (Chama Cha Wananchi) or CUF [Ibrahim Haruna
LIPUMBA]
Party of Democracy and Development (Chama Cha Demokrasia na
Maendeleo) or Chadema [Freeman MBOWE, Chairman]
Revolutionary Party of Tanzania (Chama Cha Mapinduzi) or CCM [Samia
Suluhu HASSAN, Chairman]
<note title="note">only parties with seats in the National Assembly listed</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="International organization participation">ACP, AfDB, AU, C, CD, EAC, EADB, EITI, FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD,
ICAO, ICC (NGOs), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO,
IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), MIGA,
MONUSCO, NAM, OPCW, SADC, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO,
UNIFIL, UNISFA, UNMISS, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO,
WMO, WTO</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation in the US">
         <note title="chief of mission">Ambassador Elsie Sia KANZA (since August 2021)</note>
         <note title="chancery">1232 22nd Street NW, Washington, DC 20037</note>
         <note title="telephone">[1] (202) 884-1080, [1] (202) 939-6125, [1] (202) 939-6127</note>
         <note title="FAX">[1] (202) 797-7408</note>
         <note title="email address and website">ubalozi@tanzaniaembassy-us.org</note>https://tanzaniaembassy-us.org/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Diplomatic representation from the US">
         <note title="chief of mission">Ambassador (vacant); Deputy Chief of Mission Robert Adrian RAINES (since March 2023)</note>
         <note title="embassy">686 Old Bagamoyo Road, Msasani, P.O. Box 9123, Dar es Salaam</note>
         <note title="mailing address">2140 Dar es Salaam Place, Washington, DC  20521-2140</note>
         <note title="telephone">[255] (22) 229-4000</note>
         <note title="FAX">[255] (22) 229-4721</note>
         <note title="email address and website">DRSACS@state.gov</note>https://tz.usembassy.gov/</subsection>
      <subsection title="Flag description">divided diagonally by a yellow-edged black band from the lower
hoist-side corner; the upper triangle (hoist side) is green and the
lower triangle is blue; the banner combines colors found on the
flags of Tanganyika and Zanzibar; green represents the natural
vegetation of the country, gold its rich mineral deposits, black
the native Swahili people, and blue the country's many lakes and
rivers, as well as the Indian Ocean</subsection>
      <subsection title="National symbol(s)">Uhuru (Freedom) torch, giraffe; national colors: green, yellow,
blue, black</subsection>
      <subsection title="National anthem">
         <note title="name">"Mungu ibariki Afrika" (God Bless Africa)</note>
         <note title="lyrics/music">collective/Enoch Mankayi SONTONGA</note>
         <note title="note">adopted 1961; the anthem, which is also a popular song in Africa, shares the same melody with that of Zambia but has different lyrics; the melody is also incorporated into South Africa's anthem</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="National heritage">
         <note title="total World Heritage Sites">7 (3 cultural, 3 natural, 1 mixed)</note>
         <note title="selected World Heritage Site locales">Ngorongoro Conservation Area (m); Ruins of Kilwa Kisiwani and Songo Mnara (c); Serengeti National Park (n); Selous Game Reserve (n); Kilimanjaro National Park (n);</note>Stone Town of Zanzibar</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Economy">
      <subsection title="Economic overview">emerging lower middle-income East African economy; resource-rich
and growing tourism; strong post-pandemic recovery from
hospitality, electricity, mining, and transit sectors; declining
poverty; stable inflation; gender-based violence economic and labor
force disruptions</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP (purchasing power parity)">$159.326 billion (2021 est.)

$152.788 billion (2020 est.)

$149.798 billion (2019 est.)
<note title="note">data are in 2017 dollars</note>country
comparison to the world: 75</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP growth rate">4.28% (2021 est.)

2% (2020 est.)

5.8% (2019 est.)country
comparison to the world: 111</subsection>
      <subsection title="Real GDP per capita">$2,600 (2021 est.)

$2,600 (2020 est.)

$2,600 (2019 est.)
<note title="note">data are in 2017 dollars</note>country
comparison to the world: 201</subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP (official exchange rate)">$60.633 billion (2019 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Inflation rate (consumer prices)">3.69% (2021 est.)

3.29% (2020 est.)

3.46% (2019 est.)country
comparison to the world: 126</subsection>
      <subsection title="Credit ratings">
         <note title="Moody's rating">B2 (2020)</note>
         <note title="note">The year refers to the year in which the current credit rating was first obtained.</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by sector of origin">
         <note title="agriculture">23.4% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="industry">28.6% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="services">47.6% (2017 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="GDP - composition, by end use">
         <note title="household consumption">62.4% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="government consumption">12.5% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="investment in fixed capital">36.1% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="investment in inventories">-8.7% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports of goods and services">18.1% (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports of goods and services">-20.5% (2017 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Agricultural products">cassava, maize, sweet potatoes, sugar cane, rice, bananas,
vegetables, milk, beans, sunflower seed</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industries">agricultural processing (sugar, beer, cigarettes, sisal twine);
mining (diamonds, gold, and iron), salt, soda ash; cement, oil
refining, shoes, apparel, wood products, fertilizer</subsection>
      <subsection title="Industrial production growth rate">6.5% (2021 est.)country
comparison to the world: 67</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force">29.863 million (2021 est.)country
comparison to the world: 22</subsection>
      <subsection title="Labor force - by occupation">
         <note title="agriculture">66.9%</note>
         <note title="industry">6.4%</note>
         <note title="services">26.6% (2014 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Unemployment rate">2.65% (2021 est.)

2.53% (2020 est.)

2.22% (2019 est.)country
comparison to the world: 27</subsection>
      <subsection title="Youth unemployment rate (ages 15-24)">
         <note title="total">4.6%</note>
         <note title="male">3.7%</note>
         <note title="female">5.5% (2021 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 190</subsection>
      <subsection title="Population below poverty line">26.4% (2017 est.)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Gini Index coefficient - distribution of family income">40.5 (2017 est.)country
comparison to the world: 55</subsection>
      <subsection title="Household income or consumption by percentage share">
         <note title="lowest 10%">2.8%</note>
         <note title="highest 10%">29.6% (2007)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget">
         <note title="revenues">$7.873 billion (2017 est.)</note>
         <note title="expenditures">$8.818 billion (2017 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Budget surplus (+) or deficit (-)">-1.8% (of GDP) (2017 est.)country
comparison to the world: 100</subsection>
      <subsection title="Public debt">37% of GDP (2017 est.)

38% of GDP (2016 est.)country
comparison to the world: 145</subsection>
      <subsection title="Taxes and other revenues">11.7% (of GDP) (2018 est.)country
comparison to the world: 180</subsection>
      <subsection title="Fiscal year">1 July - 30 June</subsection>
      <subsection title="Current account balance">-$1.122 billion (2020 est.)

-$1.512 billion (2019 est.)

-$2.262 billion (2018 est.)country
comparison to the world: 137</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports">$8.555 billion (2020 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars

$9.659 billion (2019 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars

$8.307 billion (2018 est.)country
comparison to the world: 112</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - partners">India 15%, United Arab Emirates 15%, Switzerland 14%, Uganda
12%, China 7% (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exports - commodities">gold, cashews, copper, precious metals, legumes (2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports">$9.181 billion (2020 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars

$10.576 billion (2019 est.) note: data are in current year
dollars

$10.399 billion (2018 est.)country
comparison to the world: 118</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - partners">China 34%, India 15%, United Arab Emirates 12% (2019)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Imports - commodities">copper, refined petroleum, packaged medicines, palm oil, wheat
(2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Reserves of foreign exchange and gold">$5.05 billion (31 December 2018 est.)

$5.888 billion (31 December 2017 est.)

$4.067 billion (31 December 2016 est.)
<note title="note">excludes gold</note>country
comparison to the world: 101</subsection>
      <subsection title="Debt - external">$22.054 billion (2019 est.)

$20.569 billion (2018 est.)country
comparison to the world: 91</subsection>
      <subsection title="Exchange rates">Tanzanian shillings (TZS) per US dollar -

2,297.764 (2021 est.)

2,294.146 (2020 est.)

2,288.207 (2019 est.)

2,263.782 (2018 est.)

2,228.857 (2017 est.)</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Energy">
      <subsection title="Electricity access">
         <note title="electrification - total population">40% (2019)</note>
         <note title="electrification - urban areas">71% (2019)</note>
         <note title="electrification - rural areas">23% (2019)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity">
         <note title="installed generating capacity">1.623 million kW (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">6,522,440,000 kWh (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">0 kWh (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">113 million kWh (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="transmission/distribution losses">974 million kWh (2019 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Electricity generation sources">
         <note title="fossil fuels">65% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="nuclear">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="solar">1.3% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="wind">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="hydroelectricity">32.8% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="tide and wave">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="geothermal">0% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="biomass and waste">1% of total installed capacity (2020 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Coal">
         <note title="production">712,000 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">577,000 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">126,000 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">0 metric tons (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="proven reserves">269 million metric tons (2019 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Petroleum">
         <note title="total petroleum production">0 bbl/day (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="refined petroleum consumption">52,800 bbl/day (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil and lease condensate exports">0 bbl/day (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil and lease condensate imports">0 bbl/day (2018 est.)</note>
         <note title="crude oil estimated reserves">0 barrels (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - production">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 206</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - exports">0 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 207</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refined petroleum products - imports">67,830 bbl/day (2015 est.)country
comparison to the world: 69</subsection>
      <subsection title="Natural gas">
         <note title="production">1,378,773,000 cubic meters (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="consumption">1,378,773,000 cubic meters (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="exports">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="imports">0 cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
         <note title="proven reserves">6.513 billion cubic meters (2021 est.)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Carbon dioxide emissions">11.491 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)
<note title="from coal and metallurgical coke">1.32 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="from petroleum and other liquids">7.466 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>
         <note title="from consumed natural gas">2.705 million metric tonnes of CO2 (2019 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 101</subsection>
      <subsection title="Energy consumption per capita">3.334 million Btu/person (2019 est.)country
comparison to the world: 178</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Communications">
      <subsection title="Telephones - fixed lines">
         <note title="total subscriptions">72,469 (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 145</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telephones - mobile cellular">
         <note title="total subscriptions">47,685,200 (2019)</note>
         <note title="subscriptions per 100 inhabitants">82.21 (2019)</note>country
comparison to the world: 32</subsection>
      <subsection title="Telecommunication systems">
         <note title="general assessment">Tanzania’s telecom sector enjoys effective competition, particularly in the mobile segment; the government has encouraged foreign participation to promote economic growth and social development, and policy reforms have led to the country having one of the most liberal telecom sectors in Africa; the government has sought to increase broadband penetration by a range of measures, including the reduction in VAT charged on the sale of smartphones and other devices, and reductions in the cost of data; the MNOs became the leading ISPs following the launch of mobile broadband services based on 3G and LTE technologies; operators are hoping for revenue growth in the mobile data services market, given that the voice market is almost entirely prepaid; the MNOs have invested in network upgrades, which in turn has supported m-mobile data use, as well as m-money transfer services and banking services. Together, these have become a fast-developing source of revenue; the landing of the first international submarine cables in the country some years ago revolutionized the telecom market, which up to that point had entirely depended on expensive satellite connections; the government aims to complete a national fiber backbone network, having signed an agreement; in late 2021, the government announced plans to extend the national backbone network from about 8,300km to 15,000km by 2023, and to provide ongoing connectivity to more countries in the region (2022)</note>
         <note title="domestic">fixed-line telephone network inadequate with less than 1 connection per 100 persons; mobile-cellular service, aided by multiple providers, is increasing rapidly and exceeds 86 telephones per 100 persons; trunk service provided by open-wire, microwave radio relay, tropospheric scatter, and fiber-optic cable; some links being made digital (2020)</note>
         <note title="international">country code - 255; landing points for the EASSy, SEACOM/Tata TGN-Eurasia, and SEAS fiber-optic submarine cable system linking East Africa with the Middle East; satellite earth stations - 2 Intelsat (1 Indian Ocean, 1 Atlantic Ocean) (2019)</note>
         <note title="note">the COVID-19 pandemic continues to have a significant impact on production and supply chains globally; since 2020, some aspects of the telecom sector have experienced a downturn, particularly in mobile device production; progress toward 5G implementation has resumed, as well as upgrades to infrastructure; consumer spending on telecom services has increased due to the surge in demand for capacity and bandwidth; the crucial nature of telecom services as a tool for work and school from home is still evident, and the spike in this area has seen growth opportunities for development of new tools and increased services</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadcast media">according to statistics from the Tanzania Communications
Regulatory Authority (TCRA), Tanzania had 45 television stations as
of 2020; 13 of those stations provided national content services
(commercially broadcasting free-to-air television); there are 196
radio stations, most operating at the district level, but also
including 5 independent nationally broadcasting stations and 1
state-owned national radio station; international broadcasting is
available through satellite television which is becoming
increasingly widespread; there are 3 major satellite TV providers
(2020)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet country code">.tz</subsection>
      <subsection title="Internet users">
         <note title="total">13,141,527 (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="percent of population">22% (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 48</subsection>
      <subsection title="Broadband - fixed subscriptions">
         <note title="total">1,135,608 (2020 est.)</note>
         <note title="subscriptions per 100 inhabitants">2 (2020 est.)</note>country
comparison to the world: 70</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transportation">
      <subsection title="National air transport system">
         <note title="number of registered air carriers">11 (2020)</note>
         <note title="inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers">91</note>
         <note title="annual passenger traffic on registered air carriers">1,481,557 (2018)</note>
         <note title="annual freight traffic on registered air carriers">390,000 (2018) mt-km</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Civil aircraft registration country code prefix">5H</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports">
         <note title="total">166 (2021)</note>country
comparison to the world: 33</subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with paved runways">
         <note title="total">10</note>
         <note title="over 3,047 m">2</note>
         <note title="2,438 to 3,047 m">2</note>
         <note title="1,524 to 2,437 m">4</note>
         <note title="914 to 1,523 m">2 (2021)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Airports - with unpaved runways">
         <note title="total">156</note>
         <note title="over 3,047 m">1</note>
         <note title="1,524 to 2,437 m">24</note>
         <note title="914 to 1,523 m">98</note>
         <note title="under 914 m">33 (2021)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Pipelines">311 km gas, 891 km oil, 8 km refined products (2013)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Railways">
         <note title="total">4,097 km (2022)</note>
         <note title="standard gauge">421 km (2022)</note>
         <note title="narrow gauge">969 km (2022) 1.067 m gauge</note>
         <note title="broad gauge">2,707 km (2022) 1.000 m guage</note>country
comparison to the world: 44</subsection>
      <subsection title="Roadways">
         <note title="total">145,203 km (2022)</note>
         <note title="paved">11,201 km (2022)</note>
         <note title="unpaved">134,002 km (2022)</note>country
comparison to the world: 35</subsection>
      <subsection title="Waterways">1,594 km (2022) (Lake Tanganyika 673 km, Lake Victoria 337 km,
and Lake Nyasa (Lake Malawi) 584 km are the principal avenues of
commerce with neighboring countries; the rivers are not
navigable)country
comparison to the world: 53</subsection>
      <subsection title="Merchant marine">
         <note title="total">314</note>
         <note title="by type">bulk carrier 4, container ship 6, general cargo 144, oil tanker 49, other 111 (2021)</note>country
comparison to the world: 51</subsection>
      <subsection title="Ports and terminals">
         <note title="major seaport(s)">Dar es Salaam, Zanzibar</note>
      </subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Military and Security">
      <subsection title="Military and security forces">Tanzania People's Defense Forces (TPDF or Jeshi la Wananchi la
Tanzania, JWTZ): Land Forces, Naval Forces, Air Force, National
Building Army (Jeshi la Kujenga Taifa, JKT), People's Militia
(Reserves); Ministry of Home Affairs: Tanzania Police Force
(2022)
<note title="note 1">the National Building Army is a paramilitary organization under the Defense Forces that provides 6 months of military and vocational training to individuals as part of their 2 years of public service; after completion of training, some graduates join the regular Defense Forces while the remainder become part of the People's (or Citizen's) Militia</note>
         <note title="note 2">the Tanzania Police Force includes the Police Field Force (aka Field Force Unit), a special police division with the responsibility for controlling unlawful demonstrations and riots</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Military expenditures">1.1% of GDP (2021 est.)

1.2% of GDP (2020 est.)

1.1% of GDP (2019 est.) (approximately $810 million)

1.2% of GDP (2018 est.) (approximately $800 million)

1% of GDP (2017 est.) (approximately $690 million)country
comparison to the world: 126</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military and security service personnel strengths">approximately 25,000 active duty personnel (21,000 Land Forces;
1,000 Naval Forces; 3,000 Air Force) (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military equipment inventories and acquisitions">the TPDF's inventory includes mostly Soviet-era and Chinese
equipment; in recent years, China has been the leading supplier of
arms to the TPDF (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military service age and obligation">18-25 years of age for voluntary military service; 6-year
commitment (2-year contracts afterwards); selective conscription
for 2 years of public service (2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military deployments">450 Central African Republic (MINUSCA); 850 Democratic Republic
of the Congo (MONUSCO); 125 Lebanon (UNIFIL) (May 2022)</subsection>
      <subsection title="Military - note">in 2021-2022, Tanzania contributed troops to the Southern
African Development Community (SADC) intervention force that was
assisting the Mozambique Government's fight against Islamic
militants</subsection>
      <subsection title="Maritime threats">the International Maritime Bureau reports that shipping in
territorial and offshore waters in the Indian Ocean remain at risk
for piracy and armed robbery against ships</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Terrorism">
      <subsection title="Terrorist group(s)">Islamic State of Iraq and ash-Sham - Mozambique (ISIS-M)
<note title="note">details about the history, aims, leadership, organization, areas of operation, tactics, targets, weapons, size, and sources of support of the group(s) appear(s) in</note>Appendix-T</subsection>
   </section>
   <section title="Transnational Issues">
      <subsection title="Disputes - international">Tanzania-Burundi: none identifiedTanzania-Democratic Republic of the Congo: none
identifiedTanzania-Kenya: none identifiedTanzania-Malawi: dispute with Malawi over the boundary
in Lake Nyasa (Lake Malawi) and the meandering Songwe River; Malawi
contends that the entire lake up to the Tanzanian shoreline is its
territory, while Tanzania claims the border is in the center of the
lakeTanzania-Mozambique: none identifiedTanzania-Rwanda: none identifiedTanzania-Uganda: none identified</subsection>
      <subsection title="Refugees and internally displaced persons">
         <note title="refugees (country of origin)">126,241 (Burundi), 80,360 (Democratic Republic of the Congo) (2022)</note>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Illicit drugs">significant transit country for illicit drugs in East Africa;
international drug-trafficking organizations and courier networks
transit through Tanzania to smuggle heroin and methamphetamine from
Southwest Asia; produces cannabis products and khat for domestic
consumption and regional and international distribution;
traffickers influence politicians, law enforcement, and others in
positions of power with money</subsection>
   </section>
</country>
